좋습니다.
Cool.
여러분 안녕하세요. CME 295 3강에 오신 것을 환영합니다.
Hello, everyone, and welcome
to lecture 3 of CME 295.
오늘은 정말
기대되는 날입니다.
So today is a very
exciting day, because we're
오늘 드디어 대규모 언어모델을
소개할 예정입니다.
going to finally introduce
large language models.
그 전에, 본격적으로 시작하기에 앞서
But I guess before we
go into that I'm just
늘 그렇듯이 공지사항부터
먼저 전해드리겠습니다.
going to start, traditionally,
with some announcements.
몇몇 분들이 수업 전에
슬라이드를 받고 싶어 하셨는데요,
So some of you wanted to have
the slides before the class.
혹시 슬라이드를 받아서
So just a heads up
that in case you
필기를 하거나 메모하려는 분들은
want to use the slides
to do some annotations,
슬라이드가 지금 웹사이트에
업로드되어 있습니다.
they're on the
website right now.
편하게 다운로드해서 사용하시면 됩니다.
So feel free to get them.
그리고 Shervin과 함께
정기적으로,
And with Shervin, we'll try
to, just on a regular basis,
매주 목요일 저녁마다 슬라이드를
웹사이트에 올리려고 합니다.
every Thursday evening, have
them publish on the website
다운로드해서 자유롭게
필기하실 수 있도록 하겠습니다.
so that you can download
them and annotate.
좋습니다.
Cool.
이제 본격적으로 시작하겠습니다.
So with that, let's start.
언제나처럼 지난주에 다룬 내용을
간단히 복습하겠습니다.
And as usual, we're going to
recap last week's episodes.
기억하신다면 1강과 2강은
So if you remember,
lecture 1 and lecture 2
셀프 어텐션 개념을 소개하고
were all about introducing
the concept of self-attention
그것이 트랜스포머 구조와
어떻게 연결되는지 다뤘습니다.
and linking them to the
construct of the transformer.
그리고 지난 시간에는 다양한 모델의
유형을 살펴봤고,
And what we did last lecture was
look at all the types of models
그 모든 모델이 트랜스포머 기반이라는
점도 알아봤습니다.
that are out there
and how they were all
즉, 트랜스포머를 바탕으로 하고 있습니다.
based on the transformer.
크게 세 가지 범주가 있는데요,
So there are three categories,
three main categories of models.
첫 번째로 살펴본 것은
인코더-디코더 모델이었습니다.
So the first one that we saw
was encoder-decoder model,
기본적으로 트랜스포머를
기반으로 하고 있습니다.
which basically relies
on the transformer.
트랜스포머의 인코더와
It has the encoder
of the transformer,
트랜스포머의 디코더를 모두 사용하죠.
the decoder of the transformer.
이런 모델들은 주로 입력이 텍스트인
작업에 쓰입니다.
And typically, the tasks
there are input text.
즉, 텍스트를 입력받아 텍스트를 출력합니다.
So text in, text out.
예를 들면 T5와 그 다양한 변형 모델들이 있습니다.
So we saw that one example
was T5 and all the variations.
두 번째 유형의 모델은
The second type
of model is where
트랜스포머에서 디코더를 제거하고
we remove the decoder
from the transformer
인코더만으로 구성된 모델을 사용하는 경우입니다.
and we obtain an
encoder-only model.
그래서 우리는 BERT처럼
So we went deeper
into BERT, which is
대표적인 인코더 전용 모델을 더 깊이 살펴봤습니다.
the typical encoder-only model.
또한 BERT가 가진 특징 중 하나는,
And I guess, we
also saw that what
임베딩이 입력을 매우 잘 표현하고,
BERT has is this nice
property that it's encoded
의미가 풍부하다는 점입니다.
embeddings are very meaningful
and expressive of the inputs.
이러한 성질을 활용한 예로는 분류나
And so we saw the example
of classification,
감정 추출 작업이 있습니다.
sentiment extraction.
구체적으로는,
So what we did
was, in particular,
CLS 토큰의 인코딩된 임베딩을
take into consideration
the encoded embedding
활용한다는 점을 확인했습니다.
of the CLS token.
실제로 BERT는 문서나
So I guess in real life, BERT
is used to encode documents
문장을 임베딩하는 데 주로 사용됩니다.
to encode sentences.
이러한 모델들이 어떻게 유용하게 쓰이는지는
And we're going to
see later in the class
뒤에서 더 자세히 알아볼 예정입니다.
how these models are useful.
그리고 마지막으로
And then last but
not least, we have
세 번째 범주의 모델은 디코더 전용 모델입니다.
the third category of models,
which is decoder only.
트랜스포머에서 디코더 부분만 남겨둡니다.
So we only keep the decoder
part of the transformer.
여기서는 또 약간의 변형이 들어갑니다.
And so here, we also do a
little bit of a modification.
예를 들어, 이제 더 이상 필요하지 않으므로
So we remove the
cross-attention because we
크로스 어텐션을 제거합니다.
don't need it anymore.
인코더가 없기 때문입니다.
We don't have an encoder.
이런 종류의 모델 역시 텍스트 입력과 텍스트 출력을 사용합니다.
And these kinds of models
are text in, text out.
대표적인 예로 GPT 같은 모델을 들 수 있습니다.
And so GPT is a very good
example of such models.
실제로 요즘 대부분의 모델이 디코더 전용 모델입니다.
And actually, most models these
days, they're decoder-only.
정리하자면,
모델의 주요 분류는 이 세 가지입니다.
So these are the
three main kinds
다양한 곳에서 이런 모델들을 볼 수 있습니다.
of models that you
can see out there.
여기까지 모두 괜찮으신가요?
So far so good for everyone?
좋습니다.
Cool.
이제 LLM이라는 용어를 소개하겠습니다.
So with that, I'm going
to introduce the term LLM.
LLM은 대규모 언어모델, Large Language Model의 약자입니다.
So LLM stands for
large language model.
그렇다면 대규모 언어모델이란 무엇일까요?
So what is a large
language model?
우선 대규모 언어모델은
So first of all, a
large language model
언어모델입니다.
is a language model.
언어모델이란 토큰의 시퀀스에
확률을 할당하는 모델입니다.
So a language model is a
model that assigns probability
즉, 여러 토큰의 나열에 대한 확률을 예측하는 것이죠.
to sequences of tokens.
이 경우에 우리 모델은 항상
So in this case,
our model always
다음 토큰이 나올 확률을 예측합니다.
predicts the probability
of the next token.
이런 관점에서 볼 때 이것이 바로 언어모델입니다.
So it's, in that sense,
a language model.
그리고 대규모 언어모델은 말 그대로 '대규모'라는 특징도 있습니다.
But also, a large
language model is large.
그렇다면 왜 '대규모'일까요?
So why is it large?
이제 이런 모델들이
실제로 얼마나 커졌는지 살펴보겠습니다.
So we're going to see
that these models,
모델 크기 자체가
엄청나게 커졌습니다.
they are actually scaled
up in terms of size.
먼저 모델의 사이즈 측면에서 보면,
So first of all in
terms of model size.
요즘은 수백억에서 수천억 개 파라미터를 가진
So these days, it's not
uncommon to see models
그런 규모의 모델들도 흔히 볼 수 있습니다.
on the order of hundreds
of billions of parameters.
보통 LLM이라고 하면
But typically,
when we say LLM we
최소한 10억 개 이상의 파라미터가
say at least on the
order of a billion.
이런 모델들은 엄청난 양의 데이터로
학습이 진행되었습니다.
These models, they've also been
trained on a huge amount of data
여기서 데이터 양이란,
and hereby amount of
data, we quantify that
사전학습에 사용된 토큰의 개수로 계산합니다.
by the number of tokens that
they were pre-trained with.
이 숫자는 보통
And this is on the
order of magnitude
수천억 개에서
of hundreds of
billions of tokens
심지어 조 단위의 토큰에 이르기도 합니다.
or even trillions of tokens.
가장 큰 모델들은
수십 조 개 토큰을 사용합니다.
So I think the biggest ones are
like on the tens of trillions
정말 어마어마한 규모죠.
of tokens.
즉, 엄청나게 방대한 학습 데이터셋이 필요합니다.
So huge training sets.
그리고 이 모델들은 많은 연산 자원이 필요하기 때문에 규모가 큽니다.
And they're also large because
they need a lot of compute.
보통 여러 개의 GPU가 있어야 제대로 동작할 수 있습니다.
So typically you need a bunch
of GPUs to make them work.
하지만 최근에는 최적화가 많이 진행되어서
Although these days there's
been a lot of optimizations
소비자용 GPU에서도 동작할 수 있도록 많은 개선이 이루어졌습니다.
to have them work on
consumer based GPUs.
이 부분은 뒤에서 다시 살펴보겠습니다.
So we're going to
see that later on.
결론적으로 LLM은 이런 기준들에 따라 크다고 할 수 있습니다.
But in LLM is large according
to these categories.
그리고 또 한 가지 짚고 넘어가고 싶은 점이 있습니다.
So another thing that
I want to point out
지금 이야기하는 이런 용어들은 사실 비교적 최근에 등장했습니다.
is that all these terminologies,
they're relatively new.
제가 기억하기로 2018년이나 2019년만 해도
So I remember in
2018, '19, there was
LLM이라는 개념 자체에 뚜렷한 정의가 없었습니다.
no real definition of an LLM.
사실 그때는 LLM에 대해 이야기하는 사람도 거의 없었죠.
I think no one actually
talked about LLMs.
초기에는 LLM이라고 하면
In the beginning, maybe
people talked about LLMs.
BERT 같은 모델도 포함했었습니다.
They included BERT.
하지만 BERT는 인코더 전용 모델로
But Bert is an
encoder-only model
텍스트를 생성하지는 않습니다.
that does not produce text.
그래서 현재의 LLM 정의에 따르면
So with the current
definition of an LLM,
이제는 비교적 명확히 기준이 정해졌죠,
which right now has been
pretty well established,
BERT는 텍스트를 생성하지 않으므로 LLM으로 분류되지 않습니다.
BERT would not be an LLM
because it doesn't produce text.
그래서 여기서 다루는 언어모델은
So here, we only
consider language models
텍스트에서 텍스트로 변환하고, 크기가 매우 크며,
that do text to text, that are
very large in size, in terms
사전학습에 사용된 데이터의 양이나
of amount of data that have
been trained on and in terms
연산 자원 면에서 모두 큰 모델입니다.
of compute.
좋습니다.
Cool.
앞서 봤듯이, 이러한 모델들은 디코더 전용 구조를 가지고 있습니다.
And as we saw before, these
models are decoder-only.
여기서는 인코더 부분을 제거하고,
So here, what we do is
we remove the encoder,
마스킹된 셀프 어텐션만 남겨둡니다.
we only keep the
masked self-attention,
그리고 피드포워드 신경망,
the feedforward neural
network, and then the addition
그리고 덧셈과 정규화 연산만 남게 됩니다.
and normalization.
즉, 이 구조만 유지하는 것이죠.
So we only keep this.
이 구조가 바로 LLM의 백본이 됩니다.
And this is the
backbone of LLMs.
GPT가 좋은 예라고 말씀드렸는데요,
And so I mentioned GPT is
kind of a good example.
하지만 그것만 있는 건 아닙니다.
But it's not just that.
이 외에도 다양한 모델들이 있습니다.
You have plenty of other models.
Meta의 LLaMA, 그리고 Gemma,
So you may have heard of
LLaMA from Meta, Gemma
Google의 Gemma, DeepSeek, Mistral, Qwen 등도 있죠.
from Google, DeepSeek,
Mistral, Qwen, and so on.
이 모델들의 목록은 매우 많습니다.
The list is long.
대략 말씀드리면,
I would say roughly--
요즘 나오는 LLM의 90% 이상이
I mean, more than 90%
of modern day LLMs,
전부 디코더만 사용하는 구조입니다.
they're all decoder-only.
이 점을 꼭 기억해 두시면 좋겠네요.
So I think that's
something to keep in mind.
좋습니다.
Cool.
네.
OK.
이제 LLM이 어떤 구조로 만들어지는지 알게 되었죠.
So now you how LLMs are made of.
하지만 요즘에는 여기에
다른 요소들도 추가되고 있습니다.
But there is something else
that people these days also
바로 이런 것들이 새롭게 도입되고 있습니다.
introduce to these models.
이제 곧 그 내용을 함께 살펴보겠습니다.
And we're going to
see that in a bit.
이 모델들이 매우 큰 규모라고 말씀드렸죠.
So I mentioned that
these models are
보통 수백억 개 이상의 파라미터를 가지며,
huge in size, again,
typically hundreds of billions
정말 방대한 수의 파라미터를 사용합니다.
of parameters.
그래서 단순히 한 번 추론을 하는 데에도
상당한 연산이 필요합니다.
So it takes a lot of compute
to just compute one inference,
그리고 이런 모델을 학습시키는 데에도 많은 계산이 필요하죠.
or also to train these models.
그런데 여러분은 이렇게 생각할 수도 있습니다.
But you may wonder,
do you really
정말 모든 파라미터가
항상 다 활성화될 필요가 있을까요?
need to have all
these parameters be
간단한 예측, 즉 forward pass에서
모든 파라미터를 써야 할까요?
activated during a forward pass,
to make a simple prediction?
여기서 하나의 비유를 들어 보겠습니다.
So I'm going to have
a little metaphor.
여러분이 한 방에 들어간다고 가정해 봅시다.
So let's suppose
you enter in a room.
그 방에는 수학자, 물리학자,
And in the room, there is a
mathematician, a physicist,
화학자, 그리고 역사가가 있다고 해봅시다.
a chemist and a historian.
여러분이 이 강의실에 들어오는 셈이죠.
So you come in
this class, there's
각 분야의 전문가들이 여러 명 앉아 있습니다.
a bunch of people who are
expert in what they do.
여러분이 어떤 질문, 예를 들어 수학 질문이 있다고 해봅시다.
And you have a question,
you have a math question.
그렇다면 여러분은 이 질문을 누구에게 할 건가요?
So a question I have for you is,
who would you ask your question?
수학자에게 질문하겠죠?
Would you ask the mathematician?
아니면 화학자에게 물어볼 건가요?
Would you ask the chemist?
혹은 모두에게 질문하겠습니까?
Would you ask everyone?
사실 우리는 지금, 모두에게 질문을 하고 있습니다.
Well, right now,
we ask everyone.
모델의 모든 파라미터에게 질문을 던지죠.
We ask all parameters
of the model
생성 과정의 계산에 모두가 관여하게 됩니다.
to be involved in the
computation of the generation.
그래서 여기서 중요한 아이디어는, 어떤 입력을 받았을 때
And so the idea here
is given an input,
꼭 모두에게 질문할 필요는 없다는 것입니다.
maybe it's not necessary
to ask everyone
계산에 모두가 참여하지 않아도 될 수 있겠죠.
to be involved in
the computation.
그래서 실제로는 모델의 일부만
So the idea is let's actually
just have a subset of the model
다음 토큰의 계산에 관여하도록 하자는 것입니다.
be involved in the
computation of the next token.
즉, 이런 '전문가' 개념을 소개하려는 거예요.
So I'm just introducing
this idea of experts.
이제 다음과 같은 표기법을 도입해봅시다.
So let's suppose
we're introducing
표기법을 새로 소개할게요.
the following notation.
n명의 전문가가 있다고 가정합시다.
So let's suppose
we have n experts.
수학자, 화학자처럼 생각하시면 돼요.
So think of it as your
mathematician, your chemist,
역사학자 등 무엇이든 될 수 있습니다.
historian, whatever.
이들이 바로 여러분의 전문가들이죠.
So these are your experts.
입력 x가 주어졌을 때, 여러분은 스스로에게 묻습니다.
And the idea is given an input
x, you're going to ask yourself
출력 생성을 위해 누가 참여해야 할까 하고 말이죠.
who should be involved in the
generation of the outputs.
그래서, 예를 들어 또 다른 네트워크가 있습니다.
So you're going to have,
let's say, another network.
여기서는 이를 게이트(G)라고 부르겠습니다.
Where we're going to
call it G like gates,
게이트 또는 라우터(router)라고도 불립니다.
but it's also sometimes
called router.
어떤 게이트가 있어서, 그 게이트가 우리에게 알려줍니다.
So let's suppose we have
some gates that tells us
어떤 전문가가 추론에 참여해야 하는지 말이죠.
which experts should be
involved in the inference.
이런 시스템이 있다고 가정합시다.
So if we have that,
so let's suppose here,
게이트가 실제로 이렇게 알려주는 겁니다. 예를 들어 2번 전문가가
the gate tells us OK, so
actually, expert number 2
여러분의 질문에 가장 잘 답할 수 있다고요.
is well suited to
answer your question.
여기서 아이디어는 입력이 그 전문가에게만
흘러가고 다른 전문가들에게는 가지 않는다는 것입니다.
So here, the idea is
that the input is just
즉, 입력이 해당 전문가에게만 전달되고,
다른 전문가들에게는 전달되지 않습니다.
going to flow into that expert,
but not the other experts.
이 구조에는 이름이 있습니다.
So this has a name.
이것을 mixture of experts, 즉 전문가 혼합 모델이라고 합니다.
It's called mixture of experts.
줄여서 MoE라고 부르기도 합니다.
So it's denoted MoE.
모두가 MoE에 대해 이야기하죠.
Everyone talks about MoE.
이 구조들이 바로 mixture of experts, 즉 MoE입니다.
So these are a
mixture of experts.
그리고 자주 보게 되는 수식이 있습니다.
And so the formula that you
will see a lot is this one.
출력 y, 즉 y hat은
So the output y,
which is denoted y hat
각 전문가의 출력을 어떤 값으로 가중합한
결과가 됩니다.
is the sum of the expert output
weighted by some quantity, which
이 가중치는 게이트의 출력으로,
각 전문가의 중요도를 알려줍니다.
is the output of the
gate, which tells you
즉, 각 전문가의 출력이 얼마나 중요한지를 나타냅니다.
how important the output
of each expert is.
네, 그렇습니다.
Yeah.
좋은 질문입니다.
Great question.
질문은 G를 어떻게 학습시키냐는 것입니다.
So the question is,
how do you train G?
E를 어떻게 학습시키냐는 부분도 있는데,
How do you train
E. So typically,
보통은 이 둘을 동시에 학습시킵니다.
you train them jointly.
이 부분은 조금 있다가 다시 다루겠습니다.
So we're going to see that
maybe in a little later.
그냥 일반적인 학습 과정과 비슷하게 생각할 수 있습니다.
But you can think of it
as just training as usual.
포워드 패스를 하고, 손실을 계산하고,
You do your forward pass,
you compute the loss
그다음에 역전파를 합니다.
and you backprop.
이게 흥미로운 질문인 이유는
And it's actually an
interesting question
MoE를 학습할 때 생기는 여러 도전과제가 있기 때문입니다.
because there is some challenges
that come with training MoEs
이 부분은 바로 뒤에서 살펴보겠습니다.
that we're going
to see in a second.
네, 맞습니다.
Yeah.
질문은 이 E들이 무엇이냐는 것이었습니다.
Question is, what are these E's.
이 E들의 구조가 어떻게 되냐는 질문이죠.
What is the architecture
of these E's?
지금은 그냥 어떤 네트워크라고만 생각합시다.
So let's suppose right now
that there's just some network.
아직 구체적으로 정의하진 않았지만,
We're not specifying
them for now,
이 부분도 곧 자세히 살펴보겠습니다.
but we're going to
see this in a second.
일단 지금은 어떤 신경망이라고 가정해봅시다.
Let's suppose for now,
it's some network.
좋아요.
Cool.
네.
OK.
제가, 만약 모든 전문가를 활성화하지 않는다면 어떨까 라고 말씀드렸죠.
So I told you that what if
we don't activate everyone.
일부만 활성화한다면 어떻게 될까요?
What if we activate a subset?
그런데 이 수식은, 사실,
But this formula,
actually, I guess,
모든 전문가의 출력을 다 고려한다고 가정하고 있습니다.
assumes that we're actually
considering all expert outputs.
여기서 두 가지 형태의 MoE를 구분해야 할 것 같아요.
So I just want to distinguish
two kinds of MoEs.
첫 번째는 dense MoE라고 불리는 형태입니다.
So there's one kind that
is called a dense MoE.
dense MoE는
So a dense MoE
actually does not have
참여하는 전문가 수에 아무 제약이 없습니다.
any constraints on the number
of experts that are involved.
그래서 이런 가중치는 0과 1 사이 아무 값이나 될 수 있어요.
So these weights, they can
be anywhere between 0 and 1.
즉, 확률분포로 생각하면 됩니다.
So think of them as a
probability distribution.
다만 어떤 전문가에 더 많은 가중치를 줄 수도 있죠,
But it's just going to put more
weight towards some experts
다른 전문가들과 비교했을 때 말이죠.
compared to others.
아까 예시로 돌아가서, 수학 질문이 있다고 해볼게요.
So back to the example that
I had, so let's suppose
그래서 제가 수학자에게 물어볼 겁니다.
I have a math question.
수학자, 화학자, 그리고 역사학자에게요.
So I'm going to ask
the mathematician,
이렇게 세 명에게 묻는다고 해 보죠.
the chemist, the historian.
아마도 수학자가 말하는 것에 더 높은 가중치를 주겠죠,
So I'm probably going
to add a higher weight
예를 들어 역사학자보다 말이죠.
to what the mathematician
says compared
역사학자와 비교해서요.
to let's say, the historian.
이게 바로 핵심 아이디어입니다.
So this is the idea.
그런데 여기서
흥미로운 점이 하나 있습니다.
But then the
interesting thing is
우리가 활성화하는 전문가 수를
when we constrain
the number of experts
제한하게 되면,
that are activated,
because here,
아까 말했듯이, 우리가 관심 있는 건
as we mentioned
previously, what we're
모든 전문가를 참여시키지 않고
interested in is to
not involve everyone
계산량을 절약하는 데 목적이 있습니다.
is to make some savings in the
amount of compute that we do.
그래서 MoE에는 또 하나, sparse MoE라는 형태가 있습니다.
So there's a second kind of MoE
that's called the sparse MoE.
이 방식은 말 그대로,
And what it does is it only
selects the quote unquote,
'상위 k개의' 전문가만 선택합니다.
"top k" experts.
여기서 k는 1일 수도 있습니다.
So k can be equal to 1.
즉, 하나의 전문가나, 때로는 두 명까지 선택할 수도 있죠.
So one expert or even two.
이 k값은 여러분이 선택하는 하이퍼파라미터입니다.
So it's a hyperparameter
that you choose.
따라서 여기서 출력은
And so here, the
expression of the output
선택된 모든 전문가에 대해
becomes the sum over
all the chosen experts
G(x) 곱하기 E(x)의 합으로 표현됩니다.
of a G of x times E of x.
여기까지 괜찮으신가요?
So far, so good?
좋습니다.
Cool.
물론 이 외에도 더 많은 내용이 있습니다.
And of course, there's
a lot more to it.
더 자세히 알고 싶으면
So in case you are
interested in learning more,
슬라이드 하단에 있는 자료를
feel free to go into
the resources that
자유롭게 참고하셔도 됩니다.
are at the bottom of the slide.
그리고 한 가지 더 말씀드리면,
So one thing that I
will say is that we
연산량을 측정하는 단위가 있습니다.
have a unit of measure
of the amount of compute
이러한 모델이 각 pass마다 생성하는 연산량을 나타냅니다.
that these models
produce for each pass.
여러분은 FLOPS라는 용어를 보셨을 겁니다.
So you will see the term FLOPS.
혹시 FLOPS라는 용어를 본 적 있나요?
So have you seen the
term FLOPS out there?
아마 거의 없을 겁니다.
No, not really.
이 FLOPS는 부동소수점 연산(floating-point operations)을 의미합니다.
So it stands for
floating-point operations.
즉, 얼마나 많은 연산이 이루어지는지를 정량화하는 거죠.
So it quantifies
how many operations.
덧셈이나 곱셈 같은 연산이라고 생각하시면 됩니다.
Think of it as additions,
multiplications
예를 들어 하나의 forward pass에서 이런 연산이 일어나게 됩니다.
are involved in a
forward pass let's say.
결국 FLOPS는 과제가 얼마나 많은 연산을 요구하는지 나타내는 척도가 됩니다.
And it basically quantifies
how compute heavy is your task.
그래서 일반적으로 우리가 말할 때는,
So typically, what
we say is when
dense MoE가 아니라 sparse MoE를 사용하면,
we go through a sparse MoE
as opposed to a dense Moe,
FLOPS 양이 더 적습니다.
we have a lower amount of FLOPS.
이처럼 FLOPS가 단위로 사용됩니다.
So this is the unit of
measure that you will see.
이제 다시 아까 질문으로 돌아가 보겠습니다. 과연 전문가란 무엇일까요?
But back to your question,
so what are these experts?
10분 전에 저희가 LLM은
디코더 전용 모델이라고 말씀드렸죠.
So if you remember, I mean, 10
minutes ago, we said that LLMs,
LLM은 디코더 전용 모델입니다.
they are decoder-only models.
여기서 여러분께 질문 하나 드리겠습니다.
So I have a question for you.
만약 우리가 LLM에 MoE를 넣고 싶다고 가정해봅시다.
Let's suppose we wanted to
put some MoEs in our LLM.
그렇다면 그걸 어디에 넣어야 할까요?
Where would we put it?
여기서 선택지는 세 가지가 있습니다.
So here, I guess, we
have three choices.
첫 번째는 마스킹된 셀프 어텐션 레이어가 있고,
We have the masked
self-attention layer.
두 번째는 피드포워드 신경망이 있습니다.
We have the feedforward
neural network.
그리고 마지막으로 정규화(normalization)가 있습니다.
And then we have
this normalization.
여기서 여러분이라면 MoE를 어디에 넣으시겠습니까?
So question for you, I guess,
where would you put this?
어디가 가장 복잡한 부분이라고 생각하시나요?
I guess, where do you think is--
즉, 네트워크에서 연산이 가장 많은, 가장 복잡한 부분이 어디일까요?
I guess, the most complex
parts of the network.
연산량이 많은 곳이 어디일까요?
Where is there a
lot of operations?
피드포워드라 생각하시나요?
Feedforward?
네, 맞습니다.
Yes.
네.
Yeah.
좋은 답변입니다.
Great answer.
네, 실제로 피드포워드 신경망이 그 부분입니다.
So it's indeed the
feedforward neural network.
그 이유는 Shervin이 강의 1에서 언급했는데요,
And the reason for that is I
think Shervin mentioned it,
아마 강의 1에서 이야기했던 것으로 기억합니다.
I think, in lecture 1.
기억하신다면 피드포워드 신경망은
So if you remember, the
feedforward neural network
D차원 입력 벡터가 들어오고,
is a network such that
you have the input, which
이 입력이 D차원의 벡터로 표현됩니다.
is your D-dimensional
input vector.
그리고 나서 이것이 예를 들어
And then you have this being
projected into, let's say,
DFF 차원 공간으로 투영됩니다.
a DFF dimensional space.
그 다음 다시 D차원 공간으로 되돌아오게 됩니다.
And then it goes back to the
D-dimensional, I guess, space.
즉, DFF는 보통 입력 차원보다 더 큽니다.
So the DFF is typically larger
than your dimension of, I guess,
여기서 입력보다 더 크다고 할 수 있죠.
the inputs.
여기서 입력이라고 말한 부분이 바로 이 부분입니다.
When I say input, it's here.
그래서 보통은 DFF 차원이 더 큽니다.
So it's typically larger.
그래서 여러분이
이 피드포워드 신경망에서 가지게 되는 파라미터의 수는
So the amount of
parameters that you
이 피드포워드 신경망에
포함된 파라미터의 양은
have in that feedforward
neural network
대략적으로 D 모델 곱하기
DFF 곱하기 2에 해당하는 규모이고,
is something on the order of
magnitude of D model times
여기에 일부 편향(bias)이 더해집니다.
DFF times 2 plus some bias.
그러니까 사실상,
파라미터 수는 이 정도 규모라고 볼 수 있습니다.
So it's basically your
order of magnitude.
그리고 어텐션 레이어도
기억하신다면,
And the attention
layer, if you remember,
주로 프로젝션 행렬들로
구성되어 있습니다.
it's basically composed of
the projection matrices,
이 프로젝션 행렬들의 차원이
어떻게 되는지 살펴보면,
what is the dimension of
the projection matrices.
D 모델 곱하기 쿼리, 키, 값
각각의 차원에 해당하게 됩니다.
So it's D model
times the dimension
즉, 키의 차원 또는 쿼리,
값의 차원과 연결되는 구조입니다.
of keys to dimension of queries
the dimension of values.
그리고 이 차원은
보통 훨씬 더 작습니다.
And this dimension is
typically much lower.
보통 100 이하 정도로 생각하시면 됩니다.
So think of it over 100.
그래서 D 모델은 보통 O(100)이나 O(1,000)
정도로 설정됩니다.
So your D model is typically
O over 100, O over 1,000.
프로젝션 부분에서 DFF는
O(1,000),
And then the projection here,
the DFF is O over 1,000,
또는 O(10,000) 정도까지 확장됩니다.
O over 10,000.
좋습니다.
Cool.
자, 이제 모두가
이 부분이 mixture of experts를
So is everyone now
convinced that this
적용하기에 좋은 위치라고
납득하셨죠?
is a good way, good place to
put the mixture of experts?
네?
Yeah?
좋습니다.
Cool.
실제로도 이렇게
구현이 됩니다.
So this is actually
how it's done.
요즘 LLM에서는 이 전체가 아니라
일부만 연산에 참여하는 것이 일반적입니다.
So in modern day LLMs, this
idea of not involving everyone
즉, 다음 토큰 예측 계산에
모든 유닛이 관여하는 것이 아니라,
in the computation of
the next token prediction
mixture of experts를
적절히 배치하는 식이죠.
is such that you would
put the mixture of experts
즉, 함수 f_n을
이 위치에 넣는 방식입니다.
where the fn is
just basically here.
그리고 보통은
sparse mixture of experts를 사용합니다.
And typically you would have
a sparse mixture of experts.
아까 질문 주신 내용으로 돌아가서,
여기서의 expert들은
So back to your question,
so these experts
사실상 피드포워드
신경망입니다.
are actually feedforward
neural network.
그래서 여러 개의 네트워크를
학습할 수도 있지만,
So you would have several
networks that you can train,
실제로는 한 개만 활성화하게 됩니다.
but you would only activate one.
그래서 보통 k는 1로 설정합니다.
So typically, k
would be equal to 1.
물론 k를 2로 둘 수도 있지만,
이 경우 일부 전문가만 사용하게 됩니다.
It can be also equal to 2 but
it would only be a subset.
제가 말하고 싶은 요점이 바로 이겁니다.
So that's my point.
그리고 이 라우팅은 토큰 단위로 이루어집니다.
And this routing would be
done at the token level.
디코더를 떠올려보면,
입력값을 받아들이죠.
So if you remember, the
decoder, it basically
즉, 여러 개의 토큰을 받게 됩니다.
takes something as inputs.
여러 개의 토큰이 입력으로 들어오는 거죠.
So a bunch of tokens.
여기서 제가 말하고 싶은 것은, 각 토큰마다
And here, what I'm
saying is that each token
서로 다른 전문가가 해당 토큰을
처리할 수 있다는 점입니다.
will be processed by
an expert that may be
즉, 각 토큰마다 선택되는 전문가가 다를 수 있습니다.
different from the other token.
여기서 라우터는 토큰의 표현을 받아서,
So the router here would take
the representation of the token
어떤 전문가가 가장 적합한지
결정하게 됩니다.
as input and figure out
which expert should be best
즉, 이 토큰이 어떤 전문가로 전달될지 라우터가 결정하는 겁니다.
for this token to flow towards.
이 개념이 이제 이해가 되시나요?
Does this idea make sense?
이후에 이 부분을
도움이 될 만한 그림으로 설명하겠습니다.
So I have a little
illustration later
잠시 후에 그림을 통해 좀 더 설명드릴게요.
on that hopefully will help.
이제 이 모델을 어떻게 학습하는지에 대한 질문으로 돌아가겠습니다.
So now back to your question
about how you train this model.
라우터를 따로 학습해야 할까요?
Do you train the
router separately?
전문가 네트워크를 따로 학습해야 할까요?
Do you train the
experts separately?
사람들이 겪는 주요 과제 중 하나는,
So one challenge
that people have
이렇게 MoE 기반 모델을 학습할 때,
is when they train these
MoE-based models, to make sure
모든 전문가가 일정하게
사용되도록 만드는 것입니다.
that all experts are, I guess,
having a weight, are being used.
모델을 학습하다 보면
Because it's very possible
that you train your model
어떻게든
한두 개의 전문가만 계속 활성화될 수 있습니다.
and that somehow
only, I don't know,
항상 같은 일부 전문가만
선택될 수 있다는 뜻이죠.
one or two experts
always get activated.
그리고 나머지 전문가들은
계속 비활성화돼 있습니다.
And the other one, they
always are inactive.
즉, 계산에 전혀 참여하지 않는 경우도 있습니다.
They are never involved
in the computation.
이런 문제를 라우팅 붕괴(routing collapse)라고 부릅니다.
So this problem is
called routing collapse.
그렇다면 왜 라우팅 붕괴라고 부를까요?
So why is it called
routing collapse?
그 이유는 라우터가 항상 똑같은
전문가만을 선택하기 때문입니다.
It's because the
router always chooses
특정 전문가들만 선택되고, 다른 전문가들은 선택되지 않습니다.
some experts, but not others.
이것이 하나의 과제입니다.
So this is a challenge.
이 문제를 해결하려는 방법은
And the way people
try to mitigate
손실 함수에 일부 항을 추가해서
이 문제를 완화하는 것입니다.
this challenge is by
changing the loss function
여기 나와 있는 것처럼,
손실 함수에 추가 항을 더합니다.
and adding it some extra
term, which is written here.
기본적으로 추가하는 항은
하이퍼파라미터 알파에
So it's basically some
hyperparameter alpha times
전문가의 수와 어떤 값들의
합을 곱한 형태입니다.
the number of experts
times the sum of quantities
이 값들은 토큰이 해당 전문가로
분배되었는지에 따라 달라집니다.
that depend on
whether or not tokens
즉, 토큰이 어떤 전문가 i로
보내졌는지를 다 더해서 구합니다.
went to a certain expert's
eye, and then summed
그리고 이 값을 모든 전문가에 대해 합산합니다.
over all experts.
이 수식이 완전히 이해되지 않아도
크게 중요하지는 않습니다.
So it's not super important
that you completely understand
정확히 수식이 어떻게 동작하는지
깊게 알 필요는 없습니다.
exactly how that formula works.
여기서 꼭 기억해야 할 점은,
The only thing that I think you
should take away from this slide
이 추가 손실 항이 이런 값들이
수렴할 수 있도록 도와준다는 것입니다.
is that this extra loss allows
these quantities to converge
더 균일한 분포로
가까워지는 효과가 있습니다.
more towards uniform
distributions.
이 값들이 무엇인지
다시 한번 짚고 넘어가겠습니다.
So what are these quantities,
just as a reminder.
여기서 f(i)는 토큰 중에서
So f of I is the
fraction of tokens
전문가 i로 라우팅된
토큰의 비율이고,
that are routed to
expert I. And P of I
P(i)는 전문가 i에 대한
평균 라우팅 확률입니다.
is the average routing
probability for expert I.
모든 전문가가 고르게 사용되어야 한다는 말은,
So when I say that all experts
should be used the same, what
결국 이 확률들이
I'm saying is I want
this probability to be
전문가 전체에 대해 균등하게
분포되길 바란다는 의미입니다.
kind of uniform across experts.
네, 그렇습니다.
Yeah.
여기서 질문이 있다면, 언제
So the question
is, I guess, when
이런 값들을 계산하느냐는 점일 겁니다.
do you compute these quantities?
네, 일반적인 학습 과정과
같이 생각하시면 됩니다.
So yeah, you can think of it
as a regular training process.
미니배치를 사용해서 모델을 통과시키고,
You do some mini batch,
you go through the model
그 과정에서 이러한 값들을
계산하게 됩니다.
and then you compute
all these quantities.
그리고 나서
역전파를 진행합니다.
And then what you do is
you do your backpropagation
이 값들을 기반으로
역전파가 이루어집니다.
based on that.
여기서 제가 여러분께 기억해 두셨으면 하는 점은
And I guess what I
want you to remember
이 방식이 확률에 대한 인센티브를 제공한다는 겁니다.
is that this incentivizes
the probability,
즉, 작성자의 선택이
I guess, the choice
of the writer
여러 전문가들 사이에서 더 고르게 분포하도록
to be more uniform
across experts,
유도한다는 것이죠. 이렇게 하면
which is something that
mitigates this routing collapse
라우팅 붕괴 현상을 완화할 수 있습니다.
phenomenon.
네, 맞습니다.
Yeah.
질문이 나왔는데, Dropout을 사용할 수 있나요?
So the question is,
can we use Dropout?
당연히 사용할 수 있습니다.
Of course.
항상 이런 기법들을 다른 방식들과 함께 활용할 수 있습니다.
You can always bundle that
with some other techniques.
사람들이 실제로 이것이 매우 효과적이라는 것을 발견했습니다.
So people have just kind of
found this to be very helpful.
그리고 또 다른 기법들에 대해 이야기하자면,
So speaking of other
techniques, there
아직 말씀드리지 않은 부분이 있는데,
is something that
I've not talked about,
Dropout과 매우 비슷한 아이디어입니다.
which is very similar
to the Dropout idea.
이것을 noisy gating이라고 부릅니다.
So it's called noisy gating.
noisy gating은 기본적으로 게이트에서 예측값을 얻은 뒤,
Noisy gating is basically
you have your predictions
여기에 노이즈를 더해주는 방식입니다.
from the gates, but then
you add some noise to it.
즉, 완전히 우연에 의해서
So basically, it's
by pure chance,
다른 전문가들도 계산에 참여할 수 있도록 하는 것입니다.
it just allows other experts to
be involved in the computation.
이 역시 또 다른 기법 중 하나입니다.
So it's also some
other technique.
이런 여러 가지 기법들이 있습니다.
There's a bunch of techniques.
어쨌든 Dropout은 오버피팅 같은 문제에 매우 효과적입니다.
But yeah, Dropout is indeed
quite useful for things
이 아이디어는 다양한 환경에서 응용할 수 있습니다.
like overfitting.
이러한 개념은 여러 상황에 적용할 수 있습니다.
And the idea can be reused
in different settings.
네, 그렇습니다.
Yep.
네, 맞아요.
자, 그럼 이번 질문은 어떻게 할 수 있을까요?
So the question
is, how can you--
혹시 미분 가능하냐는 의미인가요?
so do you mean differentiable?
여기서는, 어떻게 도함수를 구할 수 있는지에 대한 질문이라고 생각합니다.
So here, I guess, how do
you take the derivative.
이게 맞는 질문인가요?
Is that your question?
도함수가 어떻게 되는지,
조금 더 설명해 주실 수 있나요?
How is the derivative--
can you explain a bit more
어떤 점이 궁금하신 건가요?
what your concern is?
그러니까 이 질문에 대해 답하자면,
평균 라우팅 확률을 말하는 것 같습니다.
So I guess, to this question, so
the average routing probability.
이 값은 게이트 출력의 함수입니다.
So that one is a function
of the gate output.
그게 하나의 경우죠.
That's one.
PI요.
PI.
아마도 질문하신 건 FI에 대한 것 같네요.
So I guess, your
question is for FI.
FI에 대해서군요. 알겠습니다.
For FI, OK.
지금 당장 좋은 답이 떠오르진 않지만,
I don't have a good
answer on top of my head,
그래도 관련된 테크닉들이 몇 가지 있습니다.
but I think people
have some techniques.
요즘에는 이런 계산을 직접 할 필요도 없죠.
And these days, you just don't
even have to do this by hand.
이미 내장된 기능들이 있으니까요.
You have the built in thing.
FI에 대해서는 나중에 다시 설명드릴 수 있을 것 같아요.
So maybe I can follow
up with you for FI.
하지만 P of I의 경우,
이 부분은 꽤 명확하게 볼 수 있습니다.
But for P of I, do you see
that this one is quite clean.
게이트에서 나온 확률의 평균일 뿐입니다.
It's just the average of the
probabilities from the gates.
네.
Yeah.
그러니까 기본적으로 확률은...
So basically the probability--
게이트에서 나오는 출력 확률이
the output probability
from the gate,
벡터가 투영되는 것으로 생각할 수 있습니다.
you can think of it as just
the vector being projected
n차원 공간에 투영되는데,
on a space of n,
where n corresponds
여기서 n은 전문가의 수에 해당합니다.
to your number of experts.
그리고 소프트맥스를 통과하게 됩니다.
And then it's gone
through Softmax.
그래서 출력값들의 합은 1이 되죠.
So your output is basically
summing up to one.
그리고 각 차원은
And each of these
dimensions, they
해당 전문가와 연결된 값을
represent the
value corresponding
표현하게 됩니다.
to what expert I would
be, I guess, used for.
예를 들어 첫 번째 차원은 expert 1,
For instance, the first
dimension would be for expert 1,
두 번째 차원은 expert 2에 해당합니다.
second dimension would be
for expert 2, and so on.
그래서 이 값들의 평균을 구하면 되고,
So you just take the average
of this, and this one,
이 계산은 모든 파라미터로 표현할 수 있습니다.
you can express it from
all the parameters.
그래서 아마 이 부분은 괜찮을 것 같습니다.
So I think you should
be fine with that one.
네.
Yeah.
질문이 하나 있는데, 만약 MoE의 개수를 늘리면
So the question is if we
increase the number of MoEs,
모델 파라미터 수도 늘어나게 되나요?
does it increase the
number of model parameters?
아주 좋은 질문입니다.
So it's a great question.
사실 MoE 기반 모델의 핵심 아이디어 중 하나가 바로 이 부분입니다.
So it's actually one of the
ideas behind MoE-based models,
즉, 모델을 확장할 수 있으면서도
which is that you can scale
the model without having
추론 시에 연산량이 크게 증가하지 않는다는 것이죠.
to incur the cost of having
significantly more compute
즉, 추론 단계에서 연산량이 크게 늘지 않습니다.
at inference time.
그래서 사람들이 흔히 모델 용량(capacity)을 늘릴 수 있다고 말하죠.
So you can increase--
so people say capacity.
즉, 모델의 용량을 늘릴 수 있지만,
Can increase the
capacity of your model,
활성화되는 파라미터 수는
but you will still keep some,
I guess, like controlled amount
어느 정도 제한해서 유지할 수 있습니다.
of active parameters.
여기서 '활성 파라미터'란
And active parameters
are the parameters that
포워드 패스에서 실제 사용되는 파라미터를 의미합니다.
are used for a forward pass.
그래서 실제로는 사람들이 그 방식을 주로 사용합니다.
So yeah, people just use that.
즉, MoE의 수를 늘리면 전체 파라미터 수도 증가합니다.
So yeah, it would just increase
the number of parameters.
그래서 실제로 MoE 기반 모델 중에는
So that's why you see
some MoE-based models that
수백억 개 파라미터 모델보다 더 큰 경우도 있고,
are even bigger than
the ones that we
수천억 개에 이르는 모델까지 있습니다.
had on the order of
hundreds of billions.
심지어 파라미터 수가 조 단위에 이르는 모델도 있습니다.
We even have on the order
of trillions of parameters.
예를 들어, 여기서 제가 추천하는 논문 하나가
So for instance here,
one reading I recommend
스위치 트랜스포머(Switch Transformer)인데,
is switch transformer,
which scaled up to one point
이 모델은 파라미터 수를 1조 개 이상으로 확장했습니다.
something trillion parameters.
이처럼 파라미터 수가 확실히 더 많아집니다.
So yeah, it's definitely more.
하지만 이 논문을 읽어보시면
But that being said, so
if you read the paper,
이런 모델들이
you will also see that
these models, there
샘플 효율성(sample efficient)이 더 높다는 것도 알 수 있습니다.
are more what they
call sample efficient.
즉, 같은 성능을 내기까지 시간이 덜 걸립니다.
So they take less time
to be as good as what
즉, 적은 파라미터 모델에 비해 더 빠르게 좋은 성능을 낼 수 있습니다.
the model would have been with
a lower number of parameters.
그래서 만약 학습 곡선을
So if you draw
the training curve
학습 시간의 함수로 그려보면
as a function of
the training time,
이런 모델들이 일반적으로 샘플 효율성이 더 높다는 것을 확인할 수 있습니다.
you see that these models are
typically more sample efficient.
죄송합니다.
Sorry.
네.
Yeah.
네, 맞아요.
Yeah, exactly.
여기 있는 모든 것은 결국 트레이드오프입니다.
Everything here is a trade off.
네.
Yeah.
좋습니다.
Cool.
네.
Yeah.
질문은 각 어텐션 헤드마다
So the question is,
each attention head
여러 전문가가 존재하냐는 것이었습니다.
will have a number of experts.
사실 어텐션 헤드와는 상관없이 동작합니다.
So it's actually regardless
of the attention heads.
어텐션 헤드는 독립적으로 생각할 수 있고,
So the attention heads,
you can think of them
전문가 수와는 별개입니다.
as being independent,
something else.
그리고 전문가의 개수는 그것과 독립적입니다.
And the number of experts
is independent of that.
이해가 되시나요?
Does that make sense?
네.
Yeah.
맞아요.
Right.
좋습니다.
All right.
네.
Yeah.
질문은 각 블록마다 그 숫자가 존재하느냐는 것이었는데,
The question is whether every
block will have a number.
답은 네, 존재합니다.
The answer is yes.
그리고 일반적으로 가중치는 공유하지 않습니다.
And typically those
weights are not shared.
실제로, 예시를 곧 살펴보겠지만,
So typically, you-- so actually,
we're going to see an example.
레이어 1에는
It can very well
be that layer 1,
전문가 번호가 다를 수 있고,
there is the expert
number at all.
레이어 2에는 전문가 1번이 선택될 수도 있습니다.
Three that was chosen, but layer
2, there is expert number 1,
전부 자유롭게 할 수 있다는 뜻입니다.
and, you know, it's all free.
이 부분은 학습이 가능합니다.
It's trainable.
그래서 이제 우리가 결정해야 할 문제는
So the question
is we will decide
각 토큰이 어느 전문가를 선택할지라는 점입니다.
where the expert will go to.
이 모든 결정은 바로 이 게이트, 즉 이 값에 의해 이루어집니다.
So all of that is decided by the
gates, which is this quantity.
모든 것은 게이트에서 결정됩니다.
Everything is
decided by the gates,
이 게이트 역시 학습 가능한 가중치를 가지고 있습니다.
which has trainable weights.
즉, 입력값 x에서 n차원 공간으로의 프로젝션이라고 생각하시면 됩니다.
So you can think of this as just
some projection from the input
여기서 n은 전문가의 수입니다.
x to an n dimensional
space, where
n은 전문가(Expert)의 개수입니다.
n is the number of experts.
그러면 추론 과정에서
So the question is, at what
point during the inference
언제 이 결정이 이루어질까요?
is it decided?
자, 우리가 지금 추론 단계에 있다고 가정해봅시다.
So let's suppose we're
at inference time.
이제 그 동작 방식을 하나씩 살펴보겠습니다.
I'm going to walk you
through how it works.
먼저 입력 x가 있습니다.
So you have your x.
그리고 어텐션 메커니즘이 적용됩니다.
So you have this
attention mechanism.
이 어텐션은 디코더-only 구조이기 때문에,
So it interacts with all
tokens from the past given that
과거의 모든 토큰들과 상호작용합니다.
its decoder-only.
즉, 마스크와 같은 역할을 하는 거죠.
So it's like the mask.
이 x가 여기로 들어갑니다.
It goes here.
그리고 피드포워드 신경망 블록의 시작 부분에서
And at the beginning of the
feedforward neural network
토큰은 당연히 문맥 정보를 갖게 됩니다.
block, the token is,
of course, contextual.
즉, 이전의 다른 토큰들로부터 정보를 받게 되는 것이죠.
So it has the information
from these other tokens
왜냐하면 어텐션이 이루어졌기 때문입니다.
because it's attended.
그 다음에 이 토큰은 다시 이쪽으로 들어가게 됩니다.
And what it does
is it goes here.
즉, x가 먼저 G로 들어가고,
So x first goes into G. G
computes this probability
G에서 모든 전문가에 대한 확률분포를 계산합니다.
distribution over all experts.
그리고 여기서 우리가 사용하는 것은 sparse MoE 설정이기 때문에,
And given here that we are
in a sparse MoE setting,
상위 k개만 선택하게 됩니다.
we will only choose the top k.
일단 가장 높은 확률 하나, 즉 top1만 고른다고 가정해봅시다.
So let's suppose the top one,
just the highest probability.
이렇게 하면 어떤 전문가가 선택되는지 알 수 있습니다.
And we know which
experts this one will be.
그래서 결과적으로, 여러분은 오직
And so as a result of
that, you will only
선택된 expert의 출력 값만
compute the output
value of the expert
계산하게 되는 겁니다.
that the input was chosen.
혹시 그 부분을 좀 더 설명해주실 수 있나요?
So can you elaborate
on that actually?
네.
Yeah.
정확히 어느 부분을 말씀하시는 건가요?
At what point exactly?
셀프 어텐션 레이어 이후입니다.
So it's after the
self-attention layer.
네.
Yeah.
질문은, 서로 다른 헤드마다
So the question is, do we
have different classification
분류가 따로 있느냐는 거죠?
for different heads?
아니요.
No.
라우터는 하나뿐입니다.
So there's only one router.
질문하신 내용을 이해한 것 같아요.
So I think I understand
your question.
즉, 여러 어텐션 계산이
So your question
is, what do you do
헤드별로 병렬로 이루어질 때
given that you have different
attention computations going on
어떻게 처리하는지 물으신 거죠?
in parallel with the heads?
어텐션 레이어에는 각각 다른 헤드들이 있습니다.
So if you remember,
the attention layer
이렇게 여러 헤드가 있죠.
has these different heads.
하지만 결국에는
But at the end of
it, what it does
각 헤드의 결과를 모두 이어 붙인 후
is it concatenates all the
results from each of these heads
다시 D 모델 공간으로 투영하게 됩니다.
and then projects it once
again in the D model space.
네.
Yeah.
질문은, 그럼 서로 다른 G가 존재하나요?
So the question is, do
we have different Gs?
제가 말씀드릴 수 있는 건, G는
So the only thing I can tell
you is that the G is just
레이어마다 다르다는 겁니다.
layer specific.
레이어별로 다릅니다.
It's layer specific.
그리고 G는 학습 가능한 파라미터입니다.
It's trainable.
즉, 이 G는 이런 모든 입력을 어떻게 처리할지 직접 학습하게 됩니다.
So it's basically going to learn
how to process all these inputs.
그러니까 다시 한 번 말씀드리자면,
질문하신 것에 대해 G에 대해 말씀드릴 수 있는 건,
So the G, the only thing I
can tell you for your question
G는 각각의 레이어마다 다르다는 점입니다.
is going to be layer specific.
즉, 첫 번째 레이어에는 하나의 G,
두 번째 레이어에는 또 다른 G가 있다는 뜻입니다.
So the G is going to
be one G for let's say
이런 식으로 레이어마다 G가 다르고,
각각 학습됩니다.
the first layer, another G for
the second layer, and so on.
그리고 그 G도 학습 가능한 파라미터입니다.
And that one is
going to be trained.
좋습니다.
Cool.
네, 완벽합니다.
Great.
이제 시간을 한번 볼까요.
Looking at the time.
여기까지 다른 질문 있으신가요?
Do we have any other
questions here?
없습니다.
We're good.
네, 훌륭합니다.
Perfect.
이제 한 가지 재미있는 예시를 보여드리겠습니다.
So now I just wanted to
show you a cool thing
이건 아마 Mistral 팀에서
논문에서 보여준 것 같은데요,
that I believe the
Mistral team was
그 논문에서 실제로 이런 예시를 보여줬습니다.
showing in one of their papers.
여기에서 보여준 것은 특정 텍스트에 대해
각 토큰이 어떤 expert에 할당됐는지 나타내는 것입니다.
So what they're showing here
was for a given piece of text,
즉, 각각의 토큰이 어떤 expert에 루팅(할당)됐는지를 보여주는 거죠.
to show in which experts
each token was rooted.
이전에 말씀드렸듯이, expert는
각 레이어마다 다릅니다.
So as we noted
before, so experts
즉, 레이어마다 expert 구성이 서로 다릅니다.
are different from
one layer to another.
아마 여기서는 레이어 0에 대해 설명하는 것 같아요.
So I believe here,
for layer 0, so it's
즉, 한 레이어를 기준으로 보면 이런 식입니다.
like for one given layer.
그리고 실제로 보면, 대체로 이 토큰들이
And we do see that
roughly, these tokens,
어느 정도 고르게
여러 expert를 활용하고 있다는 것을 알 수 있습니다.
I guess, they leverage
like a uniform amount
즉, 모든 토큰이 어느 정도 균등하게 expert를 사용하고 있죠.
of experts, more or less.
여기서 원하지 않는 상황은,
What you would
not want to see is
모든 토큰이 전부 같은 색, 즉 같은 expert만 사용하는 것입니다.
to have every token
be the same color.
다행히도 그런 현상은 나타나지 않습니다.
But luckily it is not.
이런 식으로 라우팅 과정을
But yeah, so that's one cool
way of just representing
입력 텍스트를 색으로 표시해서
각 토큰이 어떤 expert로 연결되는지 시각화할 수 있습니다.
how the routing is done is
to just have your input text
바로 이런 방식으로 각 토큰이 어떤 expert에 들어갔는지 표현하는 거죠.
and just represent where
each token-- in which experts
각 토큰이 어느 전문가에게 할당됐는지를 나타내는 겁니다.
each token went.
좋습니다.
Cool.
네.
OK.
방금 살펴본 것은 현대 LLM들이 구조를 어떻게 변화시켰는지에 대한 한 가지 방식입니다.
So what we just saw was one way
that modern day LLMs changed
이러한 변화는 우리가 모델의 크기를 키우면서도
their architecture to
incorporate the fact that we may
한 번의 포워드 패스에서 드는 연산량은 늘리지 않기 위해 필요합니다.
want to scale the model, but
not increase the computation
즉, 연산 복잡도를 키우지 않는 것이죠.
complexity for one forward pass.
이걸 MoE에서 볼 수 있습니다.
And we saw that with MoEs.
그래서 최근에는 MoE 기반 LLM들이 많이 등장하고 있습니다.
So you will see a lot of
MoE-based LLMs out there.
이제 LLM이 있다는 것을 알게 되었으니,
And now what we will do is
knowing that we have an LLM,
이제 우리가 집중할 내용은--
we're going to focus on--
걱정하지 않으셔도 됩니다.
don't worry.
바로 다음과 같은 부분에 집중할 것입니다.
LLM이 어떻게 응답을 생성하는지 살펴보겠습니다.
We're going to focus on how a
response is being generated.
앞서 말씀드렸듯이, 현대 LLM들은
So remember, when I told you
that these modern day LLMs, what
입력 텍스트를 받아서 출력 텍스트를 생성하게 됩니다.
they do is they take some text
in and they have some text out.
주로 다음 토큰 예측이라는 과제를 수행합니다.
So it's typically these task
of next token prediction.
즉, 입력으로 토큰 하나가 들어오고,
So you have a token in.
예를 들어 문장 시작 토큰이 있다고 해봅시다.
So let's say,
beginning of sentence,
이 토큰이 LLM을 통과하면
you go through your
LLM and it just
다음 단어나 다음 토큰이 생성됩니다.
generates the next
word or the next token.
예를 들어 A가 나오면, 그 다음 A를 넣으면 teddy가 나오고,
So A, and then you take A,
and then it goes to teddy.
이어서 teddy bear와 같이 출력이 이어지는 식입니다.
And then teddy bear is,
et cetera, et cetera.
그런데 지금까지는 사실
But so far, we have
never really dug
어떻게 다음 토큰을 선택하는지
그 과정을 자세히 다루지는 않았습니다.
into exactly how we
chose the next token.
지금부터 우리가 할 것은
So what we're going
to do right now
실제로 다음 토큰이 어떻게 생성되는지
그 과정을 자세히 살펴보는 겁니다.
is to see exactly how we're
generating the next token.
여기서 보시면, 우리의 LLM은
So as you know,
here, our LLM is just
디코더만으로 구성된 구조입니다.
a decoder-only architecture.
여기에는 입력이 들어가는 디코더가 있고,
So here, what you have is a
decoder with your inputs here,
저쪽에는 출력이 나옵니다.
and then your output there.
잠깐 모든 과정을 생략한다고 가정해보죠.
So let's suppose for a
second that everything that's
가운데서 일어나는 부분을 모두 말이죠.
happening in the middle.
그러면 우리는 출력 확률만 얻는다고 생각할 수 있습니다.
And we're just obtaining
output probabilities
그 확률은 이런 식으로 생겼다고 볼 수 있어요.
that are going to look
a little bit like this.
즉, 하나의 토큰이나 여러 토큰의 시퀀스를 입력하면,
So given a token or some
sequence of tokens as inputs,
출력으로 확률분포가 만들어집니다.
you have an output
probability distribution
이 확률분포는 모델이 다음 토큰이 무엇일지
that represents what the
model thinks is the likelihood
얼마나 가능성이 높은지 나타냅니다.
that there will be a
next token, let's say,
예를 들어, 다음 토큰이 A, airplane, fluffy 등일 확률을 나타내죠.
that is equal to A, to
airplane, to fluffy, et cetera.
결국 이런 형태의 출력을 얻게 됩니다.
So this is what you have.
자, 여기서 질문하겠습니다.
만약 입력 시퀀스가 주어졌고
So now my question to
you is, if we told you
여기서 다음 토큰을 고른다고 할 때,
we have some sequence
as inputs and we want
모델이 실제로 확률분포를 반환한다면
to choose the next token, and
if I told you that our model is
이 확률분포를 기반으로 다음 토큰을
giving out actually a
probability distribution,
어떻게 선택할 수 있을까요?
I guess, how would you choose
the next token based on this?
잠시만요.
Sorry.
좋습니다.
Great.
최대 확률을 가진 토큰이죠.
The token with
maximum probability.
네, 맞아요.
OK, great.
그래서 첫 번째 생각은 이렇습니다.
So yes, the first idea.
최고 확률을 가지는 토큰을 그냥 고르면 됩니다.
Let's just take the token
with highest probability.
이 방법은 매우 자연스러운 접근법입니다.
So it's a very natural approach.
하지만 여러분이 ChatGPT나 Gemini 같은 것을 써보셨다면,
But I'm not sure if
you've been using things
항상 결과가 조금씩 다르게 나오는 걸 알 수 있을 거예요.
like ChatGPT or Gemini.
무엇을 물어보든지 항상 답변이 약간씩 달라집니다.
Every time you ask
something, it always
즉, 항상 최고 확률 토큰만 고른다면,
responds something that
is slightly different.
여기서 연산이 모두 결정적이기 때문에
So if you always
choose the token
항상 같은 결과가 나오게 됩니다.
with the highest probability,
given that the computation here,
결국 여기서 본 연산은 모두 정해져 있어서,
we're going to see
is all deterministic.
항상 같은 출력을 생성하게 되는 것이죠.
What that means is
you're always going
항상 확률이 가장 높은 토큰만을 선택하면,
to generate the same
thing regardless of,
같은 입력이 들어올 때마다 항상 같은 출력을 생성하게 됩니다.
I guess, with the same input.
이게 바로 첫 번째 한계입니다.
So that's one limitation.
즉, 다양성이 떨어지게 되는 거죠.
So it's not very diverse.
두 번째 문제는, 계속해서 확률이 가장 높은 토큰만 선택할 경우
The second problem is if you
choose the highest probability
매 단계마다 국소적으로는 최적이지만,
token on, I guess, iterative
basis, your locally optimal,
전체적으로 봤을 때 반드시 최적이라고는 할 수 없습니다.
but you're not necessarily
globally optimal.
이게 무슨 의미인지 살펴보겠습니다.
So what does that mean?
이를 좀 더 생각해보면,
So I guess, if you
think about it,
우리가 목표로 하는 것은 확률이 높은 출력 시퀀스를
our objective is for us to
produce a sequence, an output
생성하는 것이라고 할 수 있습니다.
sequence of tokens that is, I
guess, of a high probability.
하지만 항상 확률이 가장 높은 토큰만을 고르면,
But the problem is, if you
always choose the highest
반드시 전체적으로 가장 확률이 높은 시퀀스를 얻을 수 있는 것은 아닙니다.
probability token, you will not
necessarily obtain the highest
이게 바로 그 문제입니다.
probability sequence.
이 내용이 이해되시나요?
Are you convinced of this
statement, by the way?
예시를 들어 설명해보겠습니다.
So let me give you an example.
예를 들어 다음 토큰이 두 개 있고, 한 개는 0.8, 다른 하나는
So let's suppose you have the
next token where one token is
0.7이라고 해보죠.
0.8, the other one is 0.7.
그리고 0.8을 선택했다고 합시다.
And then you choose
to go with the 0.8.
사실 0.7이 아니라, 합이 1이어야 하니 0.2라고 가정할게요.
No, actually, it's not 0.7
because it has to sum to 1.
즉, 0.2라고 해봅시다.
So let's say 0.2.
만약 0.8로 시작하는 시퀀스를 계속 따라간다고 했을 때,
So let's suppose if you go
ahead with the sequence that
즉, 0.8로 시작하는 경우를 생각해봅시다.
starts with the
0.8, let's suppose
이후의 다른 토큰 확률들이 모두 아주 낮을 수 있습니다.
all other token
probabilities are very low.
결국 이렇게 생성된 출력 시퀀스의 전체 확률은
Basically, you will
have an output sequence
다른 경로에 비해 더 낮을 수 있습니다.
that will have a lower
probability than let's
예를 들어 다른 경로에서는 뒷부분에 더 확률이 높은 토큰들이 선택될 수도 있죠.
say, the other path, which
would, let's suppose,
즉, 후반부에 확률이 더 높은 토큰들이 예측될 경우입니다.
have higher probability
predictions in the later steps.
이 부분은 곧 실제 예시로 보여드리겠습니다.
So we're going to
see this in a second.
이게 바로 여기서 말하는 주요 아이디어입니다.
But this is the idea.
그래서 가장 높은 예측 확률을 선택하면
So if you choose the highest
predicted probability,
처음에는 괜찮은 아이디어처럼 보입니다.
it's a good first idea.
하지만 이 방법은 국소적으로는 최적일 수 있지만,
But it's locally optimal,
but not necessarily globally
전체적으로 최적이라고는 할 수 없습니다.
optimal.
그래서 바로 이것 때문에
And this is the
reason why we have
우리는 두 번째 방법을 사용하는데,
a second method that
is about keeping track
이 방법은 가장 확률이 높은 k개의 경로를 추적하는 방식입니다.
of the k most probable path.
여러분 혹시 beam search에 대해 들어보셨나요?
So I'm not sure if you've
heard of beam search.
beam search가 바로 이런 방식을 사용합니다.
So that's what beam search does.
여기서 k는 종종 beam size 또는 beam width라고 부릅니다.
So here, k, is sometimes called
the beam size or the beam width.
이러한 용어를 듣게 된다면,
So if you hear
these terms, these
단순히 우리가 추적하는 경로의 개수를 나타내는 이름입니다.
are just names that are
given to the number of paths
즉, 우리가 관리하는 경로의 수라는 뜻이죠.
that we keep track of.
이제 실제로 이 알고리즘이 어떻게 동작하는지 살펴보겠습니다.
And so this works as follows.
생성 과정을 문장 시작 토큰으로부터
So let's suppose we start our
generation with the beginning
시작한다고 가정해봅시다.
of sentence token.
그리고 다음 토큰이 무엇인지 알아내려고 합니다.
We want to figure out
what the next token is.
예를 들어, 아주 간단하게 토큰이 세 개인
So let's suppose we have here,
in this example, a very basic
예시를 생각해보겠습니다.
example like three tokens.
예를 들어, 두 개의 확률이 가장 높은 토큰이
And let's suppose the two
highest probable tokens
A와 the라고 가정해봅시다.
are A and the.
만약 k가 2라면, 우리가 할 일은
So if we have k equal to
2, what we're going to do
이 두 가지 가지(branch)를 추적하는 것입니다.
is to keep track of
these two branches.
이것이 첫 번째 단계입니다.
So that's the first iteration.
이제 두 번째 단계에서는
The second iteration
is we're going
각 가지가 다음 토큰을 예측할 확률을 살펴보고,
to look at all the probabilities
of next token prediction
각각의 토큰에 대해 다루게 됩니다.
for these two tokens.
그리고 항상 확률이 가장 높은 두 가지 경로만 남깁니다.
And we're going to always save
the two most probable paths.
예를 들어,
And here, for
instance, let's suppose
the 다음에 fluffy, 그리고 A 다음에 cute 같은 식이 될 수 있습니다.
if it's like the, and then
fluffy and then A and cute.
그래서 아까 제가 말씀드린 내용으로 다시 돌아가보면,
So back to what I
was saying earlier,
여기서 말씀드린 것은, 만약 여러분이
so what I was saying was
here, if you were choosing
확률이 가장 높은 토큰 경로를 선택한다고 하면,
the path that went along
the highest probability
예를 들어 the the 같은 경로를 따라가는 것이
충분히 일어날 수 있습니다.
token path, like the the,
it's very much possible
그리고 그 다음 토큰의 확률이
that the highest
probability token
the 다음에 오는 토큰의 확률이
훨씬 더 낮을 수 있습니다.
after there would be a
much lower probability
A 다음에 오는 경우보다 훨씬 더 낮을 수 있다는 거죠.
than the one after A.
그래서 beam search는 이런 상황을 보완하려고 합니다.
And so this is what
beam search tries to do.
더 전역적으로 최적화된 해를 찾으려는 것이죠.
It tries to have a more
globally optimal solution.
그럼 이제 계속 진행해보겠습니다.
So let's suppose
we continue that.
결국에는 다양한 가능한 선택지들과,
And then at the end of the
day, we obtain, I guess,
즉, k개의 후보 선택지를 얻게 됩니다.
a number of potential, I
guess, choices and the k
k개의 가능한 선택지가 있는 거죠.
potential choices.
그리고 그중에서 확률이 가장 높은,
And then we pick the one
that is the highest, likely,
즉, 가장 확률이 높은 시퀀스를 선택합니다.
the sequence with the
highest probability.
그래서 보통은 어떻게 하냐면,
So people typically
what they do is
각 토큰의 확률의 로그를 모두 더해서
they take the sum of the
logarithm of the probabilities
그 합을 사용합니다.
of the tokens.
그래서 이 때, 사람들이 이렇게 말합니다. 좋아요.
So what they say
is they say, OK.
이 시퀀스의 로그 확률은
So the log probability
of the sequence
각각의 다음 토큰 예측의
로그 확률을 모두 더한 값입니다.
is the sum of the
log probability
즉, 각 단계의 다음 토큰 예측의 로그 확률을 더하게 됩니다.
of each next token prediction.
예를 들어 BOS를 알고 있을 때 A의 로그 확률,
그리고 cute의 로그 확률을 더하는 식입니다.
So it's the log probability of
A, knowing BOS, and then cute,
BOS와 A를 알고 있을 때 cute의 로그 확률,
이런 식으로 계속 더해 나갑니다.
knowing BOS and A, and
so on and so forth.
그런데 이 방식에도 한 가지 한계가 있는데요.
But I just want to point out
one limitation of this approach,
토큰을 많이 생성할수록,
which is that the more you
generate tokens, the lower your,
최종 시퀀스의 확률이 점점 더 낮아집니다.
I guess, end sequence
probability will be.
왜냐하면 이 확률들은 모두 0과 1 사이의 값이기 때문에,
Because if you think about
it, all these probabilities
항상 0과 1 사이의 값이 나오게 됩니다.
are between 0 and 1.
즉, 곱해지는 형태로 생각할 수 있습니다.
So think of it like in
the multiplied sense.
예를 들어, 전체 시퀀스의 확률이
어떻게 되는지 생각해봅시다.
So let's suppose you
have the probability
이 전체 시퀀스의 확률은
결국 다음 토큰의 확률을
of the whole sequence,
which is just
계속 곱한 값이 됩니다.
a multiplication of the
probability of the next token.
1보다 작은 확률들을 계속 곱하게 될수록,
The more you add probabilities
below, like less than 1,
이 값은 점점 0에 가까워집니다.
the more this quantity
will go towards 0.
그래서 이 방식 그대로 사용하면,
So I guess this method,
as is, will prioritize
더 짧은 시퀀스를 우선적으로 선택하게 됩니다.
sequences that are shorter.
이런 이유 때문에, 빔서치에서는
And so for that
reason, beam search
이런 효과를 상쇄하기 위한
has some additional
term that basically
추가적인 항을 사용합니다.
counteracts that effects.
예를 들어 토큰 개수 분의 1에
어떤 차수를 곱하는 식이죠.
So something on the order
of 1 over number of tokens
거기에 어떤 지수를 취하게 됩니다.
to the power of something.
실제로는 이런 보정 기법을 사용해서
So in practice, there
is some technique
시퀀스 생성이 어느 정도 잘 동작하도록 만듭니다.
to make sure that things
kind of work relatively well.
좋습니다.
OK.
이제 이런 것들을 우리가 모두 이해했다고 해봅시다.
Let's suppose we figure
out all these things.
하지만 문제는 가장 확률이 높은 경로를
계속 추적해야 한다는 점입니다.
The problem is that
we need to keep track
즉, 가장 가능성 높은 경로를 저장해야 합니다.
of this most probable path.
그리고 이 과정에서 여러 저장 작업 등이 필요하죠.
We need to do all this
kind of saving, et cetera.
이것은 많은 계산을 요구합니다.
And it requires a
lot of computation.
또 한 가지는,
And the other thing
is we're still
여전히 가장 확률이 높은 경로에 관심이 있다는 점입니다.
interested in the most probable
path, which basically will lead
이렇게 하면 결국 생성되는 시퀀스는
to a sequence that is very--
모델이 가장 가능성이 높다고 생각하는 결과가 됩니다.
that the model thinks
is very likely.
하지만 때때로 우리가 원하는 것은
But sometimes what you
want is for your output
더 다양하거나 창의적인 출력을 얻는 것입니다.
to be more diverse
or more creative.
그래서 빔서치는 사실상
요즘에는 잘 쓰이지 않습니다.
So that's why beam search
is actually not something
대부분의 경우 빔서치는 사용하지 않고,
that people typically use.
머신 트랜슬레이션처럼
People use beam
search for things
정확한 결과가 필요한 상황에서만 빔서치를 사용합니다.
like machine translation,
where you actually
번역 같은 작업에서는
출력이 기존 문장과 매우 비슷해야 합니다.
need to have something
that is close to something
즉, 매우 확률이 높은 출력을 뽑아내야 하죠.
being very likely.
하지만 실제로는 세 번째 방법을 더 많이 씁니다.
But actually, people
use a third method.
이 방법은 샘플링 기법이라고도 부르죠.
And this method is called
also the sampling method.
제가 앞서 확률분포에 대해 말씀드렸는데요,
So I told you we
have a probability
토큰마다 다음에 올 확률이 존재합니다.
distribution over
tokens regarding
즉, 다음 토큰이 무엇일지에 대한 확률분포죠.
what the next token should be.
그래서 많이 쓰는 방법이,
And so what people
do is they just
그 확률분포에 따라 다음 토큰을 샘플링하는 것입니다.
sample the next token using
that probability distribution.
이해되시나요?
Does this make sense?
이 예시에서 fluffy, gentle, kind 그리고 smart 같은 단어들이
더 높은 확률로 선택될 수 있습니다.
So in this example, fluffy,
gentle, kind, and let's say
즉, 이런 단어들이 샘플링될 확률이 더 높아지는 거죠.
smart will have a higher
probability of being drawn
반면에 예를 들어 airplane처럼
적절하지 않은 단어들은 확률이 낮습니다.
as opposed to let's say
airplane, that have a lower
물론 이런 단어들이 등장할 확률도 0은 아닙니다.
probability of occurring.
0은 아니지만, 매우 낮은 확률을 가지게 됩니다.
Non-zero probability, but they
have a probability of occurring.
괜찮나요?
Cool?
여기까지 질문 있나요?
Any questions so far?
네.
Yeah.
맞아요.
Right.
그러니까 이건 학습이 아니라 추론 단계에서 쓰는 방법입니다.
So the question is it's not for
training, it's for inference.
네, 맞습니다.
Yes, correct.
응답을 생성하는 과정이라고 생각하면 됩니다.
Think of it as a
response generation.
예를 들어 이미 학습된 모델이 있다고 가정해봅시다.
So let's suppose you have
your model that is trained.
이제 원하는 것은 출력을 생성하는 것이죠.
What you want is to
generate an output.
그럼 어떻게 하겠습니까?
So what would you do?
네.
Yeah.
정확히 답변드리자면, 학습 과정에서는
So I guess, just to complete
my answer, so during training,
출력 확률에 신경을 씁니다.
what you would do is care
about the output probabilities
그리고 그 확률과 실제 레이블을 비교하죠.
and then compare them with
the actual label, which
대부분은 이렇게 실제 정답 레이블과 비교하게 됩니다.
is, most of the time,
like your hard label.
네, 이렇게 실제 레이블과 비교하게 됩니다.
And yeah, this is what
you would compare.
이번에는, LLM이 학습된 상황을 생각해봅시다.
So this one is let's suppose
you have an LLM that is trained,
이럴 때 어떻게 응답을 생성할 수 있을까요?
how would you
generate a response?
좋습니다.
Cool.
이 부분은 다 이해하셨나요?
Are on goods?
네.
Yeah.
그럼 질문은, 이런 상황에서 샘플링을 어떻게 하느냐는 겁니다.
So the question is, how do you
do sampling in this situation.
사실 이 내용은 다음 슬라이드에서 다룰 예정입니다.
So it's actually my next slides.
그 전에, 모두가
직관을 잘 이해했는지 확인하고 싶네요.
But I just want to
make sure everyone
즉, 가장 높은 확률 값을 선택하는 것이
탐욕(greedy) 디코딩이라고 합니다.
was on the same page
regarding just the intuition.
이 방식은 우리가 원하는 방법은 아닙니다.
So highest probability is
called greedy decoding.
빔 서치는 이보다는 좀 더 나은 방법입니다.
It's probably not
something that we want.
전역적으로 더 최적에 가까운 결과를 내주거든요.
Beam search is a
little bit better.
완전히 최적은 아니지만, 그 방향에 더 가깝습니다.
It's more something that
is globally optimal.
그래서 빔 서치가 더 낫긴 하지만, 다양성이 부족하죠.
It's not globally optimal
but more towards that.
창의성도 떨어집니다.
So it's better but
it lacks diversity.
그래서 우리가 하고자 하는 것은,
It lacks creativity.
실제로 각 토큰을 샘플링하는 방식입니다.
Which is why what
we want to do is
그리고 샘플링할 때는 여러 방법이 있습니다.
to actually sample each token.
특정 토큰만 샘플링하도록 제한하는 방법이죠.
And I guess, we
have a few methods
즉, 샘플링할 토큰의 종류를 미리 제한하는 겁니다.
that also restrict
the kinds of tokens
샘플링 대상이 되는 토큰을 제한하는 거죠.
that we want to sample from.
아까 언급했듯이, 확률이 매우 낮은 토큰들도 이론적으로는 샘플링될 수 있습니다.
Because I mentioned, these
very low probability tokens,
하지만 우리가 꼭 그런 결과를 원하는 것은 아닙니다.
they can still,
theoretically, be sampled.
그래서 대부분의 경우,
But it's not necessarily
something that we want.
사람들은 보통 가장 확률이 높은 토큰들만 남겨두고 샘플링합니다.
So what people do is
they typically restrict
즉, 상위 확률 토큰을 대상으로만 샘플링하는 것이죠.
the highest probability tokens
and only sample from them.
이때 많이 들어보셨을 용어가 Top-k 샘플링입니다.
So you may have heard of
this term, Top-k sampling.
Top-k 샘플링이란 용어 들어보신 분 있으신가요?
Who has heard of this term?
네, 조금 들어봤어요.
Yeah, a little bit.
그러면 어떻게 하냐면,
확률이 가장 높은 k개의 토큰을 선택합니다.
So what you do is you select
the top highest probable k--
즉, 상위 k개의 확률이 높은 토큰을 뽑아서
그 토큰들 중에서 샘플링하는 방식입니다.
so the top k highest probable
tokens and you sample from them.
예를 들어, 만약 k가 4라면
So let's suppose
if k is equal to 4,
확률이 가장 높은 4개를 골라서
you take the four
highest probable.
그 중에서만 샘플링하는 거죠.
And then you just
sample with them.
이와 비슷한 개념으로
Top-p라는 것도 있습니다.
And there's something else
that is quite similar in idea
이 Top-p라는 방식이죠.
which is called Top-p.
Top-p 샘플링은 확률이
높은 토큰들만 남기는 방법입니다.
So Top-p is that
you limit yourself
즉, 누적 확률이 일정 p 값을 넘을 때까지
확률이 높은 토큰들을 선택합니다.
to the top to the highest
probable tokens such
토큰들의 누적 확률이
that their cumulative
probability is
어떤 임계값 p를 넘을 때까지 포함하는 거죠.
more than a threshold p.
이 방식도 마찬가지로,
확률이 높은 토큰들만 남깁니다.
So again, it will
do the same thing.
즉, 결국 확률이 높은
토큰만 선택하게 됩니다.
It will select the
highest probable tokens.
하지만 아직 한 가지 남은 부분이 있는데요,
But then there is a part
that I still left out,
바로 이런 확률값을
처음에 어떻게 얻냐는 점입니다.
which is how do you obtain these
probabilities to start with?
여기서 다시 생각해 보면,
아까 저희가 그냥 확률값이 있다고 가정했었죠.
So if you remember, here, I had
mentioned that we just assume
확률이 있다고만 가정했었어요.
we have the probabilities.
확률값이 있으니
다음 토큰을 고르는 식이었습니다.
We just have them and we want to
choose what the next token is.
그런데 이제 궁금한 점은,
But now the question
that I'm asking
이제 이런 확률값을 가지고 무엇을 할지 알게 되었으니,
is now that we know what we will
do with these probabilities,
그렇다면 한 가지 질문은,
I guess, one question
is, how do you
이 확률값들을 처음에 어떻게 추정하느냐는 거죠.
obtain these probabilities
to start with.
이를 다시 생각해보면,
트랜스포머 기반 구조들은
So if you remember, these
transformer-based architecture
입력에 대한 인코더 표현을
계산하게 됩니다.
basically computes an encoder
representation of the input.
가장 마지막에 해당하는 몇 개의 레이어가
And what you have
is some final layers
도식 맨 위에 위치해 있고,
at the very top of
the figure, which
이 레이어들은 벡터를
어휘집 공간으로 사영하는 역할을 합니다.
aims at projecting the
vector into the space
즉, 어휘집 공간으로 투영해주는 것이죠.
of the vocabulary.
왜냐하면 우리가 원하는 것은 각 토큰에 대해
샘플링 확률을 알 수 있는 것이기 때문입니다.
Because what you want to
do is to have a probability
즉, 특정 토큰을 샘플링할 확률이
얼마나 되는지를 나타내는 수치가 필요합니다.
number for how probable it is
for you to sample a given token.
여기서 여러분이 해야 할 일은,
가장 상단에서 인풋을 받아서
So here, what you would
do is at the very top
아키텍처의 최상단에 있는 입력,
즉 토큰의 인코딩된 임베딩을
of the architecture,
have your input,
임베딩 벡터로 넣는 것입니다.
which is your encoded
embedding of the token.
그리고 선형 레이어를 통과하면서,
여러분의 D 모델 벡터를
Go through a linear layer, which
basically projects your D model
v 차원의 공간으로 투영하게 됩니다.
vector into a space of
dimension size of v.
그리고 궁극적으로 우리가 원하는 건 확률입니다.
And of course, what you
want is probabilities.
그래서 소프트맥스(Softmax) 레이어를
사용하게 됩니다.
So you would have
a Softmax layer,
소프트맥스 레이어는 모든 값을
확률로 변환시켜 줍니다.
which basically converts
everything to probabilities
즉, 전체 합이 1이 되도록 만듭니다.
such that everything sums to 1.
그리고 이렇게 해서 확률을 계산할 수 있는데,
And in order to compute
the probabilities,
바로 여기 적힌 이 공식이
바로 그때 사용되는 공식입니다.
this is the formula
that you would use,
이것이 바로 소프트맥스 레이어입니다.
which is the Softmax layer.
여기서 중요한 하이퍼파라미터가 있는데,
So there is a
hyperparameter that
그 부분을 여러분께 설명드리고자 합니다.
is quite important that I
want to talk to you about,
바로 'Temperature T'라는 하이퍼파라미터인데,
여기서 그것이 등장합니다.
which is the temperature T. And
so this is where it pops up.
즉, 다음 토큰이 특정 단어가 될 확률이
So you have the probability of
the next token being a given
지금 보시는 것처럼,
지수 함수로 표현됩니다.
word, which is equal
to the exponential
입력값과 해당 단어에 대한 값을
T로 나눈 후 지수화한 것입니다.
of the input with respect to
the given word over temperature.
그리고 이를 다시, T로 나눈 다른 모든
단어에 대한 지수값의 합으로 정규화합니다.
And then you normalize
that by the sum
즉, 모든 v에 대해 같은 방식으로 계산한
지수값의 합에 대해 정규화하는 것입니다.
of all the other exponential
of the quantity over t.
이제 T값이 실제로 어떻게 쓰이는지,
And now what we're going to
see is what that T is used for
그리고 그 T값이 실제로 어떤 역할을 하는지 살펴보겠습니다.
or what that T actually
does in practice.
그 전에, 한 가지 질문을 드리겠습니다.
So before we go into
that, just one question.
여러분은 응답 생성할 때
Temperature라는 개념을 들어본 적 있나요?
Has anyone heard about
temperatures when it
네, 들어본 적이 있으시군요.
comes to response generation?
좋아요.
Yeah.
좋습니다.
Cool.
이번 설명이 여러분이 Temperature가
결과에 어떤 영향을 주는지 이해하는 데 도움이 되길 바랍니다.
So hopefully that will
give you a better idea
Temperature가 결과 예측에
어떤 방식으로 영향을 주는지 살펴보겠습니다.
of how the temperature
kind of influences
온도는 출력 예측에 어떤 영향을 미칠까요?
your output predictions.
그래서 제가 여러분께
질문하고 싶은 게 있습니다.
So I guess, the
question that I want
온도가 낮을 때와 높을 때,
각각 어떤 영향을 미칠까요?
to ask you is, what would
be the impact of having
낮은 온도와 높은 온도에서
무슨 차이가 있을까요?
a low temperature versus
a high temperature?
그럼 낮은 온도에서는
다양성이 어떻게 될까요?
So low temperature would
correspond to a diverse of what?
네.
Yeah.
그 부분은 곧 설명하겠습니다.
So we will come to
that in a second.
혹시 의견이 있으신가요?
So yeah, do you have a--
낮은 온도에 대해서 말씀해 주시겠어요?
a lower temperature?
온도를 높였을 때는 어떻게 될까요?
Increase in temperature.
다시 한번, 아까 설명드렸던 내용으로 돌아가서
So I guess, back to
the explanation about,
만약 온도를 내렸을 때
I guess, lowering
the temperature
그게 어떤 영향을 미치는지
and what impact it
will do to the--
이에 대해 답변해 보실 분 있나요?
so I guess do you have a
suggested response to that?
네, 낮은 온도에 대해 말씀드리겠습니다.
I guess, lower temperature.
예를 들어 온도를 낮췄을 때,
무슨 일이 일어날까요?
Let's suppose you have a lower
temperature, what happens?
네.
Yeah.
정리하자면,
So I guess-- so the
long story short
온도가 낮으면 예측 확률 분포가 뾰족해지고,
is low temperature will
create a spiky distribution
온도가 높아지면 분포가 균일해집니다.
and then high temperature will
create a uniform distribution.
여러분이 느낀 직관이 맞았습니다.
But I guess, I think you
had the right intuition.
이 부분을 수식적으로도 한번 정리해 보겠습니다.
I'm going to maybe write this
in more mathematical terms.
좋아요.
OK.
이제, 여러분이 가지고 있는 확률을 생각해봅시다.
Let's suppose you have
your probability, which
확률은 xi를 t로 나눈 것을 지수로 올린 값이고,
분모에는 xj를 t로 나눈 값을 모두 더한 형태입니다.
is the exponential of xi over
t, over the sum of exponential
분모는 xj를 t로 나눈 값의 지수 합입니다.
of xj over t.
수식적으로도 실제로 어떻게 되는지
So just mathematically,
you can actually
증명할 수 있습니다.
prove what is happening here.
가장 큰 xi의 인덱스를 가지고 있다고 해봅시다.
So let's suppose you have
the index of the highest xi.
여기서 k라는 인덱스를 지정하겠습니다.
So let's call that k.
그리고 이제, 제가 할 일은 이 값을 기준으로 식을 정리하는 것입니다.
So let's suppose what I do is
I will factor by this quantity.
사실 여기에는 칠판 공간이 부족하네요.
So actually, here,
I don't have space.
그래서 여기서 계속하겠습니다.
So let's do here.
이제 k와 온도 t에 대한 식이 나옵니다.
So it will be ae
of k temperature.
그리고 분모에는 모든 j에 대해 지수 함수가 더해집니다.
And then here, you have the sum
of over all j of exponential
이때 각 항은 xj에서 xk를 뺀 값을 t로 나눈 꼴이 됩니다.
of xj over t minus xk over t.
여기서 제가 한 건,
So what I did is
I just multiplied
분자와 분모 모두에
the numerator and
the denominator
xk를 t로 나눈 값의 지수함수를 곱한 것입니다.
by exponential of xk over t.
즉, 분자와 분모에 모두 곱해준 것이죠.
So I multiplied numerator
and denominator.
물론 이 값들은 약분되어 사라집니다.
And of course, they cancel out.
그리고 여기 남는 것은 xi에서 xk를 뺀 값을 t로 나눈 식입니다.
But then what I have here
is xy minus xk over t.
여기서는 xj에서 xk를 뺀 값을 t로 나눕니다.
And here, xj minus k over t.
i가 k와 같아지면 이 항은 0이 됩니다.
So when i is equal
to k, this term is 0.
온도의 값과 상관없이 정확히 0이 되죠.
It's exactly 0, regardless
of the temperature.
그리고 xj에서 xk를 빼면 항상 0이거나 음수입니다.
And here, xj minus xk
is always negative or 0.
여기서 i가 k와 같으면 0을 t로 나눈 것이 됩니다.
So here, if i is equal
to k, you have 0 over t.
그래서 이 부분은 1이 되고요.
So here, it's 1.
그리고 1에다가 또 어떤 값이 더해집니다.
And then you have 1 plus--
어떤 항이 추가되는 셈이죠.
I guess, some quantity.
여기서 j 마이너스 xk를 t로 나누면, 이 값은 음수가 됩니다.
So j minus xk over t, which
is going to be negative.
그리고 t가 0으로 다가가면,
So the t going to 0.
그 항은 점점 더
So that one will be,
I guess, going to,
마이너스 무한대로 갑니다.
let's say, minus infinity.
따라서 exp(마이너스 무한대)는 0이 됩니다.
So exponential of
minus infinity is 0.
결국 남는 것은 어떤 식이냐면,
So what you will end
up with is something
i와 k가 같을 때만 0이 아닌 확률이 나오게 됩니다.
where for i equal to k, you will
have a non-zero probability.
반면 i가 k와 다르면,
But then for i not
equal to k, you
0을 0이 아닌 값으로 나눈 셈이 되니 결과가 0이 됩니다.
will have 0 over something that
is not equal to 0, which is 0.
즉, 수학적으로 보면,
exp(xk / t)로 묶어서 생각할 수 있습니다.
So just mathematically, if you
factor by exponential of xk
여기서 k는 가장 높은 값의 인덱스입니다.
over t, where k is the
index of the highest value,
가장 큰 로짓, 또는 가장 높은 활성값의 인덱스가 되겠죠.
I guess, the highest logit or
the highest activation vector,
사실, 온도가 작을 때는
이것을 통해 보여줄 수 있습니다.
can actually show that for
a small temperature, only
즉, 가장 큰 값만이 남게 된다는 것이죠.
the highest--
가장 큰 값의 인덱스가
so the index of the,
I guess, highest value
가장 스파이크가 큰,
즉, 가장 높은 확률을 갖게 됩니다.
will be the one that will be
highest probable with the spike
바로 그 부분에서요.
there.
반대로, 온도가 높아지면
And then when you have
a high temperature,
결국 전체가 균등분포처럼 보이게 됩니다.
basically it will look
like a uniform distribution
왜냐하면, t가 무한대로 커지면
모든 값이 같아지기 때문입니다.
because all these quantities, so
when t tends to plus infinity,
이 값들이 모두 0에 가까워지죠.
this tends to 0.
exp(0)은 e가 아니라,
So exponential of 0 is just e.
1이 됩니다. 죄송합니다, e가 아니라 1입니다.
Sorry, not e, 1.
즉, 1이죠.
So 1.
그래서 각 j의 개수만큼 1이 나옵니다.
So it's 1 over the number of j.
즉, 1입니다.
So it's 1.
즉, 전체 토큰에 대해
균등분포가 되는 것입니다.
So just a uniform distribution
across all the tokens
어휘집에 있는 모든 토큰에 대해서요.
of your vocabulary.
네, 맞습니다.
Yeah.
그래서 질문은, 온도가 작을 때
이걸 어떻게 해석하면 될까요?
So the question is, how
can I interpret a small--
질문은, 이것을 가우시안 분포로
해석할 수 있을까 하는 겁니다.
so the question is, can I
interpret that as a Gaussian?
제 생각에는,
I think.
사실 가우시안 분포는 x축의 값이 연속적인데,
So it's kind of tough
because Gaussian,
여기서는 x축에 연속적인 값들이 있죠.
you have some continuous
quantities in the x-axis.
하지만 여기에서는 토큰이라는 이산적인 값들입니다.
So here, you have tokens.
그래서 완전히 구분되는 값이죠.
So it's kind of discrete.
그리고 토큰들은 별도로 순서를 매길 수 있는 것도 아닙니다.
And it's not something
that you can order.
그래서 그냥 작은 온도에서는
분포가 매우 뾰족하다고 보시면 됩니다.
So I just probably interpret
that as small temperature
즉, 매우 스파이크하게 나타나는 분포가 됩니다.
is very spiky.
그래서 실제로는
일정한 토큰 집합이 선택됩니다.
So you will really have
a given set of tokens
가장 확률이 높은 토큰들이
더 자주 등장하게 됩니다.
that are the highest probable
that will appear more.
반면에 온도가 높으면,
And if you have a
high temperature,
사실상 모든 토큰들이
then basically,
tokens, even the ones
원래 가장 확률이 높지 않았던 토큰들도
that were not there to
be the highest probable,
확률이 조정되어 더 높게 됩니다.
will actually have an adjusted
probability that will be higher.
맞아요.
Yes.
그래서 이런 측면에서 보면,
어떤 스케일을 조정하는 것이라고 볼 수 있습니다.
So you can think of it as some
kind of scaling in that sense.
요약하면, 제가 말씀드리고 싶은 점은
So long story short,
what I want to tell
온도가 낮을 때는,
you is if you have
a small temperature,
다음 토큰이 가장 확률이 높은 쪽으로
유도된다는 것입니다.
it will encourage the next
token to be geared towards being
즉, 가장 높은 확률의 토큰이 선택됩니다.
the highest probable token.
그리고 온도가 높으면,
And then if you have
a high temperature,
확률분포가 더 고르게
I guess the distribution
of probabilities
거의 균등분포에 가까워집니다.
will be kind of
closer to a uniform
온도를 아주 크게 하면 그런 현상이 더 뚜렷해집니다.
if you're really increase
that temperature by a lot.
그래서 출력이 더욱 창의적으로 나올 수 있습니다.
So your output will
be more creative.
원래라면 뽑히지 않았을 토큰들도
You will have tokens
that you would have not
실제로 뽑힐 수 있게 됩니다.
drawn that would be drawn.
실제로 이게 의미하는 바는,
And so what that means
in practice, if you're
여러분이 좋아하는 LLM을 사용할 때,
with your favorite LLM.
예를 들어, 아주 창의적으로
뭔가를 쓰고 싶다고 가정해보겠습니다.
And let's suppose you
want to, I don't know,
정말 창의적인 글을 쓰고 싶다면요.
write something very creative.
이럴 땐 어떤 값을 써야 할까요?
So which one would you use?
낮은 온도를 쓸까요,
높은 온도를 쓸까요?
Would you use a low temperature
or high temperature?
높은 온도가 맞겠죠?
High temperature?
네, 맞아요.
Yes.
반대로, 더 결정론적이고
So if you want something that
is more deterministic, more,
고품질의 예측에 가까운 결과를
I guess, closer to something
that is very, I guess,
얻고 싶다면 낮은 온도를 사용하게 됩니다.
what you think would be
high quality, will use
좀 더 낮은 온도를 사용합니다.
more of a lower temperature.
여기서 한 가지 짚고 넘어갈 점은,
So one note here is that if
you have a strictly positive
온도가 0보다 크면, 모델을 같은 입력에 대해
temperature, every time you
run your model over an input,
실행할 때마다 다른 출력이 나올 수 있다는 점입니다.
you will obtain a
different output.
여기서 말씀드리고 싶은 건, 트랜스포머
So something I want to point out
is nothing in the transformer
아키텍처 자체는 확률적이지 않다는 겁니다.
architecture is probabilistic.
모든 동작은 결정적입니다.
Everything is deterministic.
유일하게 비결정적인 부분은,
The only thing that
is not deterministic
다음 토큰을 샘플링하는 과정입니다.
is how you sample
the next token.
이 부분만이 유일하게 비결정적입니다.
It's the only thing that
is not deterministic.
그럼 결정적인 출력을 원하면 어떻게 해야 할까요?
So what will you do to have
a deterministic output?
t를 0으로 설정하면 됩니다.
You have t equal to 0.
t를 0으로 하면, 출력이
T equal to 0, you know
for sure that your output
항상 하나로만 결정됩니다.
will be just one thing
and nothing else.
이게 바로 이론적으로 보장되는 성질입니다.
Well, that's what it's
the theoretical property.
하지만 실제로는, 연산 과정에서
But in practice,
you have some stuff
여러 가지 일들이 발생하기 때문에
that is happening in
the computation that
비결정적인 연산이 추가될 수 있습니다.
introduces some
non-deterministic operations.
이 내용은 이 강의의 범위를 한참 넘어가기 때문에,
It's much more advanced than
the scope of this class,
자세한 설명은 하지 않겠습니다.
much more advanced of
the scope of this class.
단지 실제로는 t를 0으로 해도,
I just want to call out that
in practice, t equal to 0,
이런 실용상의 이유로 인해
may lead to different
results because of this kind
다른 결과가 나올 수 있다는 점을 말씀드립니다.
of practical piece.
그래서 제가 추천드리는 것은,
So what I recommend.
필요하면 참고하실 수 있는 권장 읽기 자료가 있다는 점입니다.
So there's a suggested
reading in case
완전히 선택사항이니 부담 갖지 않으셔도 됩니다.
you're completely optional.
최근에 나온 좋은 아티클이 있습니다.
So there is a very
recent article
LM 추론에서 비결정성을 해결하는 내용을 다룹니다.
around defeating
non-determinism in LM inference.
관심이 있으시면 꼭 읽어보시길 추천합니다.
So I recommend that you read
it in case you're interested.
여기서 핵심 아이디어는 GPU 같은 하드웨어에서
So the high level idea is
our GPUs, our hardware,
이런 연산들을 GPU와 같은 하드웨어에서 줄여나갈 때,
when they reduce some
of these operations,
가끔은 매우 다른 스케일의 숫자들을
sometimes they are
reducing numbers that
한꺼번에 줄이게 되는 경우가 있습니다.
are on really different scales.
이 연산들이 실제로 어떤 순서로 수행되는지가
So the order at which these
operations are happening
굉장히 중요한 역할을 합니다.
is actually quite important.
그러니까, 이런 연산들의 순서가
So the idea is if
these operations
서로 다르게 일어나면,
they happen in
different order, it
서로 다른 결과가 나올 수 있습니다.
may lead to different results.
이론적으로는 완전히 같아야 하지만,
Even if in theory, it
should be exactly the same,
실제로는 다른 결과가 나오는 경우도 있습니다.
in practice, it may
not be the same.
그리고 이 기사에서는
이 직관을 아주 잘 설명해줍니다.
And this article
actually does a great job
관심 있는 분들은 읽어보시길 추천합니다.
at just explaining
the intuition.
완전히 선택사항이니,
꼭 필요하진 않습니다.
So yeah, just if you're
interested, completely optional.
좋습니다.
Cool.
제가 약간 늦긴 했는데, 마지막으로
I know I'm kind of
late, so I guess,
마지막으로 말씀드리고 싶은 점은,
last thing that I want
to say is let's suppose,
여러분이 출력 결과를
아주 특정한 포맷으로 생성하고 싶다고 합시다.
what you want to do is to
generate an output in a very
예를 들어서 JSON 포맷일 수도 있겠죠.
specific format.
즉, JSON 형태를 만들어낸다고 가정해보겠습니다.
Let's suppose a JSON format.
아주 단순한 방법은 LLM에게
JSON으로 생성해달라고 시키는 겁니다.
So I guess, a very
naive approach
그러면 LLM이 무엇인가 결과를 만들어내겠죠.
would be to tell your LLM, well,
please generate this in JSON.
그 다음에 그 결과가 올바른 JSON인지 확인합니다.
And then it produces something.
만약 올바른 JSON이 아니면,
And then you try to see
if it's a valid JSON.
다시 한 번 만들라고
If it's not, you repeat--
계속 요청해서 반복하는 방식입니다.
you just tell it
to generate again
제대로 생성될 때까지 반복합니다.
until it does something well.
이게 가장 단순한 접근 방식입니다.
So that's the first
naive approach.
두 번째 방법은 guided decoding이라고 부르는 방식이 있습니다.
Well, there is a second approach
that is called guided decoding.
이 방법은 생성 과정에서,
And what that does is during
the generation process,
유효하지 않은 다음 토큰들을
미리 걸러내는 방식입니다.
it filters out what it
calls invalid next tokens.
여기서, 제가 이 JSON을 생성하고 싶다고 가정해봅시다.
So here, let's suppose I
want to generate this JSON.
저는 첫 번째 토큰이 반드시
I know for sure that
my first token must
무엇인가를 여는 기호여야 한다는 걸 압니다.
be something that opens the--
이 영어 단어가 갑자기 생각이 안 나는데,
I forgot what the English
word was for this,
아무튼 이 괄호를 여는 기호입니다.
but it just opens the brackets.
네.
Yeah.
괄호를 여는 토큰이죠.
Open the brackets.
그래서 처음엔 이것만 쓸 수 있고,
So you can only have
this and then you
그 다음엔 프로퍼티 이름 등만 올 수 있습니다.
can only have the property
name and so on and so forth.
그리고 때로는 가능한 다음 토큰이
여러 개 있을 수도 있습니다.
And sometimes you can have more
than one permitted next token,
그럴 때는 우리의 다음 토큰 전략을 다시 적용하면 됩니다.
in which case you would go back
to our next token strategy.
네.
Yeah.
그렇다면 어떻게 다른 토큰들을 제한할 수 있을까요?
So the question is, how do
you restrict the other tokens?
이 부분에 대해 다루는 논문들이 여럿 있습니다.
So there's a bunch of
papers that go into that.
여기서는 이 내용까지는 다루지 않겠습니다.
We will not cover this.
하지만 몇 가지 참고할 만한 키워드를 드릴 수는 있습니다.
But I can give
you some pointers.
'finite state machine', 'FSM', 'context grammar' 이런 키워드로 검색해보세요.
Just type finite state
machine FSM context grammar.
이런 주제에 대해 다루는 논문들이 있습니다.
So there's a bunch of
papers that do that.
여기에서는 이 부분은 다루지 않겠습니다.
We will not cover that here.
좋습니다.
Cool.
그러면 이제 두 번째 파트로 넘어가겠습니다.
And I think with that, we
will go to the second part
셰르빈과 함께 진행하겠습니다.
with Shervin.
좋아요.
Great.
감사합니다, 압신.
Thank you, Afshin.
이제 저희가 함께 다양한 프롬프트 전략을
살펴보겠습니다.
So now, together,
we're going to look
이제 응답이 어떻게 생성되는지 배웠으니,
at different
prompting strategies.
이제 어떤 식으로 좋은 응답을 얻을 수 있는지
So now that how
responses are generated,
함께 알아보겠습니다.
we're going to see
how to get responses
그리고 어떻게 하면 좋은 응답을 끌어낼 수 있을지도 살펴볼 겁니다.
and how to get great responses.
그럼 우리 모두가 좋아하는 예제로 다시 돌아가보죠.
So let's go back to
our favorite example
우리의 귀여운 테디베어 예시로 돌아가보겠습니다.
about our cute teddy bear.
여기서 어휘 용어 하나를 소개하고 싶습니다.
So just I want to introduce
one piece of vocabulary.
어떤 입력이 주어졌을 때,
So when you have
some kind of input,
그 입력의 길이를
you have the length
of your inputs
토큰 개수로 측정합니다.
measured in number of tokens.
그리고 논문에서는
And you will see
in the literature
이 개념이 다양한 이름으로 등장하기도 합니다.
that it can have
different names.
예를 들면 context length, context size,
So you can see it called
context length, context size ,
window size라고도 부릅니다.
window size.
그리고 최신 코드 도구들, 예를 들어
And I think the
latest tools if you
Cursor 같은 코드 지원 툴에서는
code on Cursor or any
other code-assisted tool,
주로 context length라는 이름을 씁니다.
I think they call it
more context length,
하지만 이 용어들은 모두 같은 의미로,
but all these terms
are equivalent
동일한 개념을 가리킵니다.
and denote the same thing.
네, 그렇습니다.
OK.
이제 여기서 어느 정도 크기가 될 수 있는지
간단히 이야기해보겠습니다.
So now I want to take some
time to discuss what can be
이 값의 대략적인 크기에 대해서입니다.
some orders of magnitude here.
요즘의 대규모 언어모델들은
So like modern day
LLMs, they tend
보통 수만, 수십만,
혹은 수백만 개의 입력 토큰을
to be in the order of
magnitude of tens of thousands,
한 번에 입력으로 받을 수 있습니다.
hundreds of thousands or
millions of input tokens
이런 식으로 입력을 받는 것이죠.
as inputs.
그래서 가끔 새로운 LLM이
컨텍스트 길이 수치를 강조하는 경우가 있습니다.
So this is the kind
of input it can take.
이럴 때 말하는 context length의 숫자가 바로 이 값입니다.
So sometimes, you hear some
new LLM boosts some number.
즉, 한 번에 입력으로 받아들일 수 있는
최대 토큰 수를 뜻하는 거죠.
And then that number of
context length is exactly that.
이게 바로 그 의미입니다.
So it's how much tokens can it
accommodate in a single pass.
네, 좋습니다.
OK.
좋아요.
Great.
그리고 여러분이 아마 본 적이 있겠지만,
And then yeah, the
models, you have
이런 모델들의 광고를 보셨을 겁니다.
seen maybe some advertisement
of these models.
Gemini나 기타 모델들처럼요.
So I think at Gemini
and others that
이제 이 모델들은 백만 단위의 토큰까지 처리할 수 있다고 광고합니다.
are in the million territory.
그렇다면 이제 모든 게 완벽해진 걸까요?
Does that mean it's
all nice and pretty?
문맥 길이가 더 길어지면 모든 문제가 해결될까요?
If we have more context length,
is it going to solve everything?
사실 그렇지 않습니다.
Actually not.
최근에 밝혀진 현상이 하나 있는데,
There is a phenomenon
that was recently
올해 초 논문에서는 이를 'context rot' 현상이라고 불렀습니다.
dubbed as context rot in a paper
from earlier this summer, where
이 논문에서는 저자들이 직접 실험을 통해,
basically, the authors
are experimenting
모델이 정보를 찾아내는 능력을 측정했습니다.
the capacity of the
model to retrieve
이 실험은 'needle in a haystack' 방식으로 진행됐는데,
some piece of information
in a test called needle
즉, 건초 더미에서 바늘 찾기 테스트입니다.
in a Haystack.
간단히 말해, 질문을 하나 던진 뒤
So basically, they
ask some question.
점점 더 긴 텍스트에 답을 숨깁니다.
And in larger and larger pieces
of text, they bury the answer.
그리고 모델이 그 답을 찾아낼 수 있는지
And they try to look at
the capacity of the model
능력을 검증합니다.
to surface that answer.
문맥이 길어질수록,
And then you can see that with
respect to an increasing context
모델이 올바른 정보를 찾아내는 능력은
length, that ability to
ground the information
점점 더 떨어집니다.
with the answer that is
in the context decreases.
이 논문은 굉장히 흥미로운데,
And the paper I think is
a very interesting one.
문맥에 어떤 내용이 들어가는지도 함께 통제합니다.
It controls with respect to
what else is in the context.
여기서 'distractors', 즉 방해 요소라는 개념이 등장합니다.
There is a term of distractors,
where they put some noise
이러한 방해 요소가 포함되면,
and then they see
distractors basically
모델의 정보 검색 능력이 더욱 감소합니다.
contribute in decreasing
the retrieval capability.
즉, 문맥에 어떤 내용이 들어 있는지가 매우 중요합니다.
So also, what is in
your context matters.
그래서 보통 정보를 검색하는 문제를 LLM으로 풀고 싶을 때는,
So this is why in general,
when you have a retrieval
가능한 한 정확한 문맥만을
problem, where you want to
use your LLM to solve it,
모델에 제공하는 것이 좋습니다.
you have some good
incentive to try
필요한 정보에 최대한 근접한 문맥을
to target as much as possible,
the right piece of context
LLM이 볼 수 있도록 해주는 것이 중요합니다.
for your LLM to
see and predict on.
네, 여기까지입니다.
OK.
좋습니다.
Great.
네, 맞습니다.
Yep.
네.
Yeah.
질문이 뭐냐면, 컨텍스트 길이가 셀프 어텐션에서 보여지는 바로 그 길이냐는 겁니다.
So the question is, is the
context length exactly what
즉, 셀프 어텐션에서 보여주는 길이가 맞나요?
is shown during self-attention?
네, 맞아요.
Yes.
네.
Yeah.
그리고 이제 우리가 볼 내용은...
And then we're
going to see-- so I
저번 시간에 보셨듯이,
think we saw last time
that sometimes there
복잡도를 줄이기 위해 사용되는 몇 가지 기법이 있습니다.
are some tricks that are
used for the complexity
셀프 어텐션 메커니즘의 복잡도가 n 제곱이 되지 않도록 하는 거죠.
of the self-attention
mechanism not to be n squared.
그래서 이런 기법들이 복잡도를 관리할 때 사용됩니다.
So this is what is being
used to manage basically
즉, 컨텍스트 길이가 커질 때 연산 복잡도를 줄이는 방식입니다.
the complexity of
the computations
컨텍스트 길이가 늘어날수록 연산이 복잡해지니까요.
as the context length grows.
네.
Yeah.
좋은 지적이었습니다.
But great call out to that.
바로 그 부분이 핵심입니다.
That's exactly what is it about.
네.
OK.
좋아요.
Great.
질문 있으신가요?
Any questions?
다른 질문 있으신가요?
Any other questions?
네.
OK.
좋습니다.
Great.
이제 프롬프트가 보통 어떻게 구성되는지 정의해보겠습니다.
So now, let's define what do
prompts usually look like.
사실 프롬프트를 어떻게 구성해야 하는지에 관한 공식적인 이론은 없습니다.
So there is no formal theory on
how to structure a given prompt.
하지만 일반적으로 프롬프트에는 이런 주요 요소들이 들어갑니다.
But these are the main
lines that are usually found
모델에 제공되는 프롬프트에서 이런 구성요소를 볼 수 있습니다.
in prompts presented to models.
우선 컨텍스트를 설정하는 부분이 따로 있고,
So you can distinguish
a part that
여기는 그냥 상황을 설명하거나,
is setting up the context where
you just put the setting, you
모델에게 어떤 쿼리를 하고 싶은지 명확히 전달하는 부분입니다.
make it clear to the model, what
kind of query you want to issue.
그 다음에, 만약 여러분이
모델에게 시키고 싶은 작업이 있다면
Then let's say, if you
have some tasks that you
그에 맞는 지시문을 추가하게 됩니다.
want the model to perform,
you have instructions.
그리고 이런 지시문들 중에는
함수처럼 입력을 받는 것도 있습니다.
And then these instructions
are some of them function
그래서 여기에 입력값을 넣어줄 수 있죠.
that take as input something.
이렇게 입력을 추가해주는 겁니다.
So you add some inputs.
그리고 모델의 응답에서 원하는 결과를 얻으려면
And in order to get
what you want out
추가적으로 몇 가지 제약 조건을
넣을 수도 있습니다.
of the model's response, you may
want to add some constraints out
이렇게 설정하는 것이죠.
of it.
여기서 우리가 좋아하는 대표 예시로
테디베어 이야기를 들어보겠습니다.
So here, we took our favorite
example with a teddy bear.
여기서 컨텍스트는
테디베어가 어떤 상황인지입니다.
The context is what
is the teddy bear--
즉, 테디베어의 기분이 어떤지 같은 부분이죠.
basically, what is the
mood of the teddy bear?
그리고 우리 테디베어를 행복하게 만들기 위해
무엇을 해야 하는지 지시하게 됩니다.
What do we want to do in order
to make our teddy bear happy?
그리고 우리가 만들고자 하는 이야기가
어떤 상황인지에 대해 입력을 주죠.
And then we give
some input regarding
예를 들어, 이야기의 배경을
입력으로 제공할 수 있습니다.
where the story that
we want to generate is.
그리고 마지막으로
몇 가지 제약 조건을 줍니다.
And then we give
some constraints.
또 다른 예시로, 여러분이 매일 쿼리하는
LLM에서 살펴보면
If you want some other
example in the LLMs
컨텍스트는 예를 들어,
"당신은 ChatGPT입니다"와 같은 문장일 수 있습니다.
that you query every day, so the
context could be some sentence
또는 "오늘은 10월 10일입니다."
that says, you are ChatGPT.
"지금은 오후 4시 44분입니다."
We are October 10.
이런 식으로 배경 설정을 하는 거죠.
It is 4:44 PM.
사용자 쿼리와 입력이
지시문 역할을 합니다.
So you set the setup.
사용자 쿼리와 입력이
곧 지시문이 될 수 있습니다.
The instructions
can be basically
그 외에도, 제약 조건은
사용자는 직접 못 보더라도
what the user queries
alongside the inputs.
LLM에 전달되는 프롬프트에
포함될 수 있습니다.
And then constraints
might be things
예를 들어, 안전 관련 지침처럼
사용자에게는 보이지 않지만
that you don't see
as a user, but that
LLM 프롬프트에는 존재할 수 있습니다.
예를 들면,
might be present in the prompts
given to the LLM, such as safety
‘유해한 내용을 생성하지 말 것’과 같은
안전 지침이 있겠죠.
instructions.
예를 들어, 위해를 일으킬 수 있는
콘텐츠는 절대 생성하지 않아야 한다는 식입니다.
For example, do not generate
any contents that might lead
이런 식의 제약 조건이 포함됩니다.
to harm, or things like this.
그래서 LLM에 입력되는 프롬프트마다
이런 요소들이 포함되어 있다고 보시면 됩니다.
So every time you see an
input being fed to an LLM,
이 네 가지 차원을 이렇게 투영해서 생각하는 것이
I think these projections,
these four dimensions
각 요소가 어떤 목표와 연결되는지 파악하는 데 좋은 사고 모델이 될 수 있습니다.
can be a good mental model of
seeing which pieces correspond
구조 안에서 각 부분이 어떤 목표에 대응하는지 볼 수 있겠죠.
to what goal in that structure.
이해가 되시나요?
Does that make sense?
네, 좋습니다.
OK, great.
이제 우리가 LLM 입력을 할 때
So now that we know
what kind of mindsets
어떤 관점을 가질 수 있는지 알았으니까,
we might have for
inputs to an LLM,
이제 LLM에게 우리가 원하는 작업을
let's see how we can get
an LLM to do what we want.
어떻게 시킬 수 있는지 살펴보겠습니다.
And let's see how we can get
an LLM to do what we want
가중치 조정 없이도 LLM을 원하는 대로 동작하게 할 수 있습니다.
without tuning any weights.
이렇게 할 수 있는 개념이 바로 ‘in-context learning’,
And we can do so with a concept
called in-context learning,
즉, 문맥 내 학습이라는 개념입니다.
where the learning is a bit
of a term that is overloaded
여기서 ‘학습’이라는 단어는 사실 엄밀히 보면 조금 다르게 쓰이고 있는데요,
because you don't
actually learn anything
실제로 LLM의 가중치가
with respect to the
weights of the LLM,
변하는 것은 아니지만,
but you can distill some
knowledge inside of it
문맥 속에 정보를 녹여내서 원하는 작업을 수행하게 할 수 있습니다.
as part of the context in
order to do what you want.
in-context learning에는 크게 두 가지 방식이 있습니다.
So you distinguish
two main categories
두 가지 주요 범주로 나뉩니다.
of in-context learning.
먼저 첫 번째는 매우 단순한 방식입니다.
So there is one category
that is very simple.
이런 사고방식은 zero-shot이라고 부릅니다.
In mindset, it's
called zero-shot.
즉, 입력 외에는 아무런 정보도 제공하지 않는 것이죠.
It's basically you don't give
anything other than your input,
입력 쿼리만 주는 것입니다.
your input query.
LLM에게 그냥 원하는 작업을 요청하는 거죠.
You just ask the LLM to
do what you want to do.
그리고 또 다른 방식도 있습니다.
And then there is
another school of thought
few-shot learning이라고 불리는 방식인데,
called few-shot
learning, where you
LLM에게 입력과 출력 예시를
give examples of inputs
and outputs to the LLM
미리 여러 개 제공한 다음, 본인이 궁금한 입력을 요청하는 것입니다.
before asking the input
that you're interested in.
예를 들어 곰인형과 잠자리 동화 예시를 생각해보면,
So in the case of a teddy
bears and a bedtime stories, so
곰인형의 이름을 붙일 수 있겠죠.
you might name your teddy bears.
예를 들어 이름이 ‘테디’인 곰인형이 있다고 해봅시다.
So maybe you have teddy
bear that's called Teddy.
그리고 여러분이 이야기를 생성한 거죠.
And you generated a story.
그러면 쿼리를 입력하고,
생성하고 싶은 이야기도 입력합니다.
So you put your query,
you put the story
이렇게 여러 개의 예시를
함께 제공하게 됩니다.
that you want to generate, and
you give multiple such examples.
그리고 또 다른 테디베어,
예를 들어 Bob이라는 곰이 있다고 해봅시다.
And let's say you have another
teddy bear that's called Bob.
그럼 이번에는 Bob을 위한
이야기를 생성하고 싶을 수도 있습니다.
And then you want to
generate a story for Bob.
이런 예시들을 모두 넣고,
So you put all of
these examples,
그리고 LLM에게
원하는 이야기를 생성해달라고 요청하는 겁니다.
and you ask the LLM
to generate the story
여러분이 원하는 바로 그 이야기를요.
that you're interested in.
바로 이런 방식이 우리가 말하는
few-shot 설정입니다.
And then this is basically what
we call a few-shots setting.
좋습니다.
OK.
네, 아주 좋습니다.
Great.
이제 보통은,
이렇게 생성된 task의 성능을 볼 때
So now, generally, when
you look at the performance
예시를 제공하는 것이
of the resulting
task, giving examples
LLM이 원하는 task에
잘 맞게 유도해줍니다.
tends to steer the LLM
nicely into the task
여러분이 원하는 task로요.
that you're interested in.
즉, 여러분이 원하는 게 무엇인지
Just because you
have given an idea
모델에게 힌트를 주게 되기 때문이죠.
to the model of what
you are looking for.
그러면 모델은 학습 과정에서 배운 것을 바탕으로
And then it can use what it
has learned during its training
연결점을 찾아내고,
비슷하게 따라 할 수 있습니다.
process to connect the dots
and basically replicates.
하지만 당연히, 이런 예시를
But of course, you need
to gather such examples.
직접 수집해야 하기 때문에 비용이 듭니다.
So this is costly.
이런 방식은 컨텍스트 윈도에
더 많은 토큰이 필요하게 됩니다.
This will put some more
tokens in the context window.
그래서 계산 비용도
더 늘어납니다.
So you will need
to more compute.
하지만 최근 모델에서는
재미있는 트레이드오프가 있습니다.
But there is an
interesting trade
즉, 이러한 모델들은
합리적으로 더 높은 추론 능력을 갖게 되었죠.
off here that we see
in recent models.
그래서 제가 '일반적으로'라는 표현을
기울임꼴로 써놓은 이유도 여기 있습니다.
So they are gaining more and
more reasoning capabilities,
즉, few-shot 방식이 대체로 더 낫지만,
항상 그런 것은 아닙니다.
which is why I put the
generally nuance in italic here.
왜냐하면 최근의 더 나은 모델들에서는,
So they are generally better,
few-shots, but not always.
사람들이 기본적으로 지시문만
잘 구성해도
Because these days, with
these better models,
few-shot 예시를 부여할 때와
비슷하거나 더 나은 성능을
보일 수 있다는 사실을 발견했기 때문이죠.
people have seen that with
basically making the instruction
명령어를 더 잘 작성하면,
성능을 높일 수 있습니다.
better, you could
make the performance
이렇게 하면 인컨텍스트 러닝의 성능이
동일하거나 때로는 더 좋아질 수 있습니다.
of in-context learning on
par, or even better than
예시를 제공하는 것보다 더 나은 경우도 있습니다.
왜냐하면, 생각해 보면
if you provide examples, because
basically, when you think of it,
예시를 제공할 때는
모델을 주어진 유한한 예시들에 맞추게 됩니다.
when you provide examples,
you constrain your model
즉, 유한한 예제 집합 내에서
모델이 범위가 제한되는 거죠.
into given sets of
examples that are finite.
그래서 실제 추론할 때,
So when you are
at inference time,
예를 들어, 새로운 분포의 데이터에 대해
작업을 수행해야 한다고 하면,
let's say, you want to perform
a task on a distribution of data
모델이 일반화하기가 더 어려울 수 있습니다.
이때는
that has not been seen,
it is harder for the model
모델이 문맥에서 본 것에
맞추려고 하기 때문입니다.
to generalize because it
will try to align on what
즉, 이전에 본 맥락에
기준을 두게 됩니다.
it has seen in the context.
반면, 명령어를
더 추론 위주로 바꾸고,
Whereas if you turn your
instructions into something that
과정을 자연어로
설명해 주면,
is more reasoning
based, you explain
자연어로 작업 수행 방법을
설명해 주면,
how to do the task
with natural language,
모델이 자체 추론 능력을 이용해서
실제로 과제를 수행할 수 있습니다.
it can use its reasoning
abilities to actually do it.
그리고 이런 접근은 최근에
점점 더 많이 볼 수 있습니다.
And this is something that you
see more and more these days.
관련 연구 논문들도 계속
나오고 있는데,
So the literature on this, I
think, is still in progress,
예를 들어, 계획(plan)과
해결(solve) 같은 논문이
but you have some
papers like a plan
최근에 등장한 것으로 알고 있습니다.
and solve that's I
think came out recently.
이 논문에서는 LLM에게
스스로 계획을 세우고
And that shows if you ask the
LLM to plan itself and then
문제를 풀게 했을 때
매우 좋은 성능을 보였다고 합니다.
solve something, it can
have very good performance.
이처럼 상당히 흥미로운 사실입니다.
So yeah, this is an
interesting fact.
네, 그렇습니다.
OK.
좋습니다.
Great.
이제 다양한 학습 방법을 살펴봤으니,
So now that we have seen
basically the kinds of learning
이제부터는
응답 품질을 어떻게 높일 수 있는지 살펴보겠습니다.
that we have, now,
we're going to see
여기에 '체인 오브 소트(chain of thought)'라는 개념이 있는데,
what we can do to improve
the quality of the response.
연구자들이 발견한 것은
모델이 답을 내기 전에
So there is this concept
called chain of thought,
답에 대한 근거를 스스로
만들도록 요구하면,
where researchers have seen that
if you force the model to come
즉 답에 이르는 추론 과정을
거치게 하면
up with some rationale
to some answer
실제로 더 높은 성능을
낼 수 있다는 점입니다.
before actually giving it, it
would give higher performance.
이렇게 모델이 응답까지의 사고 과정을
표현하는 것을 체인 오브 쏘트라고 부릅니다.
So this is what people
call as chain of thought.
즉, 답에 어떻게 도달했는지를 보여주는 과정입니다.
It's basically what
led you to the answer.
예를 들어 여기서, 만약 여러분이 스스로에게
So here, for example,
if you ask yourself,
'이 곰 인형의 나이는 몇 살일까?'라고 물어본다고 합시다.
how old is this teddy bear?
그리고 모델이 그냥 숫자만 바로 답하도록 하면,
And if you force the model to
respond directly with a number,
곰 인형의 나이가 왜 그렇게 되는지에 대한
it might not be able
to do the connection as
연결고리를 잘 파악하지 못할 수 있습니다.
to exactly why the Teddy
bear is a given age.
반면에, 전체적인 추론 과정을 보여주면
Whereas when you give the
full chain of reasoning,
어떤 과정을 거쳐서 그런 답이 나왔는지 더 명확해집니다.
then it becomes clear as to
what led to that response.
이게 바로 이 기법의 핵심적인 사고방식이라고 할 수 있습니다.
So I think this is the main
mindset behind this technique.
이런 방법은 인컨텍스트 러닝에서도 활용될 수 있습니다.
And basically, this
is something that can
즉, 인컨텍스트 러닝에서 사용할 수 있는 기술입니다.
be used in in-context learning.
몇 개의 샘플을 제공할 때, 예를 들어
So if you give few-shot
examples, how old was this Teddy
'이 곰 인형의 나이는 몇 살인가'라는 질문에 숫자를 주고,
bear, you give some
number and then
그 쿼리 형태를 살짝 바꿔볼 수 있습니다.
you slightly change the query.
그리고 추론 과정이나 포매팅, 그리고
And then based on the
reasoning, formatting, and then
응답까지의 서술 방식을 바탕으로, LLM이
the response, the LLM can adjust
the reasoning and the response
이에 맞게 추론 과정과 응답을 조정하게 됩니다.
accordingly.
이렇게 하면 모델이 항상 답변과 함께
And it will force the model
to output some reasoning
추론 과정도 함께 출력하도록 유도할 수 있고,
alongside the response,
which shows an improvement
그 결과 지표 상에서도 더 나은 성능을 확인할 수 있습니다.
in basically metrics.
좋습니다.
OK, great.
그리고 여기서 한 가지 더 말씀드리고 싶은 점이 있습니다.
And then yeah, something
else that I want to say,
여러분이 어떤 작업을 잘하고 싶다고 가정해 봅시다.
let's say, you want to do a
task and you want to do it well.
항상 제대로 답이 안 나오는 샘플들이 있게 마련입니다.
m you will always have some
samples that do not work.
이럴 때는 그 샘플들을 디버깅할 수 있어야겠죠.
And then for them, you want
to have debugging ability.
일반적으로 LLM을 디버깅할 때는,
And usually when
you debug with LLMs,
예전 방식처럼 디버깅하지 않습니다.
you don't debug
like the old days.
모델의 가중치나 내부 구조를 들여다보는 게 아니라,
You don't look at weights at
the intrinsics of the LLM.
좀 더 해석 가능한 결과를 원하게 됩니다.
What you want is something
more interpretable
토큰 단위로 해석 가능한 결과물을
얻을 수 있게 되는 거죠.
that comes out of it
in terms of tokens.
그리고 보통 이런 기법을 사용할 때는
And usually, with
these techniques,
모델이 어떤 추론 과정을 거쳤는지
확인할 수 있습니다.
you can see the reasoning
that the model had before
특정 응답을 출력하기 전에 말이죠.
outputting a given response.
그래서 어디서 문제가 발생했는지
쉽게 디버깅할 수 있습니다.
And you can debug
basically what went wrong.
예를 들어, 곰의 나이가 내년에 몇 살이 될지 물어봤을 때
So if you ask how old will
the bear be next year.
모델의 추론 과정에서 '지금이 2019년이다'라고 나오면,
And if in the chain of thought
it says, hey, we're in 2019,
아, 내가 맥락에서 뭔가 실수했구나,
you know that somehow
in your context,
날짜를 잘못 넣었나 보다, 이렇게 알 수 있습니다.
oh, maybe I put the
wrong dates in there.
그래서 이런 식으로 역추적할 수 있습니다.
So you can trace back to--
문제의 근본 원인을 쉽게 파악할 수 있죠.
you can do some root
causing very easily.
그래서 이런 디버깅에도 활용됩니다.
So it's also used for that.
그리고 다른 기법들처럼
정확히 같은 맥락에서
And, exactly, in the same
way as other techniques
토큰 수를 늘리게 됩니다.
that increase the
number of tokens,
이 부분은 여러분이 어떤 트레이드오프를
관리해야 하는 요소입니다.
this is a trade off
that you have to manage,
토큰을 더 많이 생성해야 하니
추론 시간이 당연히 더 걸리게 됩니다.
that it will, of course, take
more time to infer because you
그만큼 토큰 생성이 필요하기 때문이죠.
need to generate more tokens.
하지만 일반적으로는
이 정도는 충분히 감수할 수 있습니다.
But typically,
we're fine with it.
COT에 대해 질문 있으신가요?
Any questions on COT?
네, 좋습니다.
OK, great.
그럼 이제 한 단계 더 나아가 보겠습니다.
So now let's take
it one step further.
COT를 더욱 강력하게 만들기 위해서
소개할 내용이 있습니다.
So I want to introduce even
to make COT even stronger,
모델을 여러 번 샘플링해서
you can sample your model.
여러 번 답변을 생성한 다음
Several times,
look at the answers
각 답변을 살펴보고
그 중에서 다수결로 결과를 고르는 겁니다.
it generates, and then do
some majority voting to select
여러 번 생성된 답변 중에
가장 많이 예측된 답을 선택하는 방식입니다.
the answer that was
predicted most of the times
이렇게 LLM이 예측한 결과를 기준으로요.
by a given LLM.
이 방식을 우리가 셀프 컨시스턴시
라고 부릅니다.
And this is what we
call self-consistency,
즉, 같은 질문을 여러 번 샘플링해서
여러 응답을 모으고,
where basically, you sample
responses multiple times
그 중에서 실제 답을
추출하는 방법입니다.
and then parse
the actual answer.
즉, 전체 추론 과정을
분리해서 생각할 수 있습니다.
So basically, you factor
out the whole reasoning
그리고 실제 정답을
정확히 겨냥해서 뽑아내려고 시도하죠.
and then try to
target the answer.
그리고 다수결 투표 방식으로
정답을 도출할 수 있습니다.
And then by majority
voting, you can come up
이렇게 하면 좀 더
견고하게 정답을 얻을 수 있습니다.
to an answer in a
more robust way.
네.
Yep.
질문은, 뭔가 벤치마크가
필요하지 않느냐는 것이었죠.
So the question is, do you
need to have some benchmark
더 좋다고 판단하려면
벤치마크가 필요하냐는 질문입니다.
to know if it's better?
네, 맞습니다.
And yes, absolutely.
논문에서는 모든 산술 문제와
수학 기반 예시 위에서 실험했어요.
I think the paper operates
on top of all the arithmetic
수학적 문제들에서
이 방법을 적용하였습니다.
and then mathematical
based ones.
그리고 이와 관련해서 또 하나의 질문은,
And I think one tangential
question to yours
정답을 어떻게 찾아내고
그 위에 다수결 투표를 하느냐는 것입니다.
is how can you locate
the answer and then do
즉, 보통은 그 부분에 대해
다수결을 적용하게 됩니다.
measure majority voting on it.
일반적으로 프롬프트에
실제 정답을 마지막에 넣으라는
So typically, you can
put into the context
지침을 추가해서
마지막에 정답이 오도록 만듭니다.
some instruction that says,
put the actual answer last.
그럼 마지막 부분만
추출하면 되겠죠.
So you can just
extract the last.
또한, 사람들은 보통
정규표현식 기반의 방법을 쓰거나
People, I think, use regex
based techniques, otherwise,
다른 방법으로 정답을 추출합니다.
to extract the answer.
또는 다른 LLM을 활용해서
정답을 추출하는 것도 가능합니다.
Or you could even think
of using some other LLM
이처럼 여러 방식을
생각해볼 수 있습니다.
to extract the answer.
항상 해결할 수 있는 방법이 있습니다.
So there is always
a way to do it.
그리고 말씀하신 것처럼,
우리가 벤치마크와
But yeah, to your point,
yes, we need some benchmark
그리고 실제 정답(ground truth) 레이블이 있어야
정말로 더 나은지 입증할 수 있습니다.
and then ground truth
labels to assert
그래야 실제로 더 나은지 확인할 수 있습니다.
that this is indeed better.
네.
Yeah.
여기서 나온 요청, 즉 질문은
So the request here--
so the question is,
같은 요청을 예시와 같이
여러 번 보내느냐는 것입니다.
is it going to be sent to
the same request as example?
일반적으로는 여러 샘플을
동시에 생성합니다.
So typically, you
sample it in parallel.
즉, 여러분의 모델에,
방금 Afshin이 언급한 것처럼
So basically, you ask your
model exactly what Afshin just
Afshin이 방금 언급한 바로 그것입니다.
mentioned.
시작 토큰(BOS)과
현재까지의 토큰들의 확률분포에서 샘플링을 합니다.
You sample from the
probability distribution of BOS
그리고 그 뒤에 올 다음 토큰을 샘플링하는 거죠.
and whatever tokens you
had, the next token.
이 과정을 여러 분기에서 동시에 수행합니다.
And you do that in several
other kind of branches.
이 모든 과정을 병렬로 진행할 수 있습니다.
And you do that, all
of that, in parallel.
그리고 마지막에는
답변을 파싱하게 됩니다.
And then you parse the
answer at the end of it.
즉, 이 과정의 지연 시간, 즉 레이턴시는
So basically, the
latency of this process
대략 가장 오래 걸리는
병렬 생성의 레이턴시와 비슷합니다.
is equal, roughly, to
the maximum latency
병렬로 생성했을 때 소요되는 최대 시간이죠.
of either parallel generation.
왜냐하면 이 모든 과정을
동시에 병렬로 처리할 수 있기 때문입니다.
Because you can do all
of this in parallel.
각각의 분기는 서로 영향을 주지 않습니다.
So none of these go into
the context of each other.
모두 병렬로 처리됩니다.
They're all done in parallel.
그리고 최종적으로
결과 답변을 얻게 됩니다.
And then you get
the final answer.
좋습니다.
OK, great.
다 이해하셨죠?
All good?
좋습니다.
OK, great.
이제 여러 가지 프롬프트 기법을 살펴봤으니,
So now that we have seen a
few prompting techniques,
이제 사람들이 고안해 낸 다양한 트릭을
함께 정리해보려고 합니다.
I want to cover together
tricks that people have come up
추론 시점에 어떻게 하면
생성 과정을 최대한 효율적으로 만들 수 있을지
with at inference time
to make the generation as
이 부분을 다루겠습니다.
efficient as possible.
현대 모델에서는
엄청나게 많은 파라미터가 있습니다.
And basically, yeah, so
in modern day models,
생성해야 할 토큰도 많죠.
you have a lot of parameters.
그럼 어떻게 하면
가장 효율적으로 이 작업을 할 수 있을까요?
You want to generate
a lot of tokens.
이 생각의 흐름을 두 부분으로 나눠서
살펴보겠습니다.
How do you do it the most
efficiently possible?
어떤 방식으로 하면 정확히 같은 계산을 하면서도
효율을 높일 수 있는지 먼저 보겠습니다.
So I want us to divide this
thought process into two parts.
우리가 고안할 수 있는 방법들을
이제 함께 살펴보겠습니다.
So we're going to see what
methods we can come up with that
정확히 동일한 계산을 하면서도
효율을 높일 수 있는 방법들입니다.
give us increased efficiency
on an exact level.
즉, 원래 해야 하는 계산을 그대로 하면서도
So you exactly do
the same computations
더 효율적으로 처리할 수 있는 방식을
적용하는 것입니다.
as you were supposed to do,
but in a more efficient way.
어떤 기술들이 사용될 수 있는지
여기에 몇 가지 힌트를 적어두었습니다.
And I put some hints as
to what kind of techniques
우리가 살펴볼 기법들에 대한 힌트도 적어뒀습니다.
we're going to explore.
그러면 이제 어떤 기법들이 있는지
함께 찾아보겠습니다.
So let's try to
look for techniques
중복을 피할 수 있는 방법이 있는지 살펴봅시다.
that avoid redundancies.
그리고 메모리를 가장 효율적으로
관리하는 방법도 고민해보죠.
Let's try to see what
we could do to manage
메모리를 최적으로 쓰는 방법이 무엇일지 생각해보겠습니다.
the memory in the best way.
또, LLM 내부의 방정식을
더 간단하게 표현할 수 있을지도 살펴보겠습니다.
And also, let's try to
see if we can reformulate
LLM 내부의 수식을 조금 더 단순하게
만드는 방법이 있는지 생각해봅시다.
the equations inside the LLM
in a way that could simplify
실제로 생성 과정을 조금 더 단순화할 수 있을지 살펴보겠습니다.
the generation in practice.
그리고 두 번째로 살펴볼 범주가 있습니다.
Then there is a second
category that we're
이 부분도 같이 다룰 예정입니다.
going to explore as well.
이쪽은 어떤 종류의 근사 방법을 써도 되는지에
집중해서 설명할 것입니다.
That is going to focus on
what kind of approximations
어느 정도 근사를 하더라도 결과의 품질을 유지하면서,
비용을 줄일 수 있는 방법을 살펴볼 거예요.
it might be fine to do,
and get a high quality
즉, 조금 더 저렴한 비용으로 좋은 답을 얻을 수 있지만,
정확도가 완벽하게 일치하지는 않는 방법들에 주목할 겁니다.
answer at a lesser cost,
but to be approximate.
그렇다면 아키텍처 차원에서
우리가 어떤 변형을 시도할 수 있을지 살펴봅시다.
So we have what kind
of variations we
임베딩에서 어떤 변형을 적용해 볼 수 있을까요?
could do on the architecture?
임베딩을 더 효율적으로 만드는 방법이 있을지 생각해봅시다.
Is there something we
could do on the embeddings
임베딩을 더 효율적으로 만들 수 있는지 살펴보고,
to make them more efficient?
그리고 토큰 예측 단계에서도
And then maybe on the
token prediction side,
토큰 예측을 더 빠르게 할 수 있는 방법이 있을지 살펴봅시다.
is there something we
could do to make it faster?
이해되시죠?
Does that sound good?
남은 시간은 약 22분 정도입니다.
So we have approximately
22 minutes.
이제 이 모든 내용을 다 다뤄보겠습니다.
We're going to try to go
through all of them here.
좋아요.
OK.
기법들을 크게 두 가지로 분류했는데요,
So I grouped the
categories of techniques
하나는 정확한 방식이고,
다른 하나는 근사적인 방식입니다.
into exact and
approximate techniques.
하지만 사실 둘을 따로따로 보기보다는,
But actually,
we're going to look
이제 한꺼번에 묶어서 볼 예정입니다.
at them in a grouped manner.
먼저 어텐션 레이어에서
어떤 기법들이 있는지 살펴본 뒤,
First, looking at
the attention layer,
거기서 적용할 수 있는 다양한 방법들을 살펴보겠습니다.
seeing what kind of techniques
we could have there.
그리고 두 번째로는,
And then in a second
part, we're going
그리고 두 번째로는 아웃풋 레이어를 살펴보겠습니다.
to look at the output layer.
그리고 토큰 생성 단계에서
무엇을 할 수 있는지도 보겠습니다.
And then see what we can do at
the level of token generation
이렇게 해서 가능한 한 결과가
좋아지도록 만들 수 있는 방법을 다루겠습니다.
to make things as
good as possible.
그럼 이제 어텐션 레벨부터 시작하겠습니다.
So let's start at
the attention level.
우리는 각 토큰마다
어떻게 동작하는지 봤었죠.
So we have seen that
for every token,
현재 토큰이 이전 토큰들에
어텐드할 수 있어야 합니다.
you need the current token to
attend to the previous ones
이게 바로 마스킹된 셀프 어텐션에서 일어납니다.
in this masked self-attention.
예를 들어, 여러분이 시퀀스를 생성한다고 해봅시다.
So let's say you
generate your sequence.
그리고 지금은 특정 토큰에 위치해 있다고 합시다.
You are at a given token.
예를 들어 "a cute teddy bear"를 생성했다고 해볼게요.
So let's say, you have
generated a cute teddy bear.
그리고 이제 "ease"라는 단어에 도달했다고 합시다.
And then now you are at ease.
이제 여러분은 "ease"에 대한 쿼리를 가지고 있게 됩니다.
Now you have the query ease.
그리고 여러분은 "ease"의 키 표현과 값 표현을
계산해야 합니다.
You will compute the key
representation and the value
왜냐하면 당연히 그 작업을 해야 하니까요.
representation of ease.
지금이 현재 토큰이니까요.
Because of course,
you have to do it.
[번역 실패] It's your current token.
It's your current token.
하지만 우리는 이미 계산해둔
이전 결과들을 재사용할 수 있으면 좋겠죠.
But we want to have a way to
reuse the past computations we
이전에 계산했던 키 표현을
다시 활용할 수 있길 바랍니다.
had done to compute
the key representation
이전 토큰의 키 표현과
값 표현을 재사용하는 것이죠.
of the previous tokens and
the value representation
이전 토큰들의 값 표현도 마찬가지입니다.
of the previous tokens.
이런 것이 우리가 달성하고 싶은 목표라는 게 이해가 되나요?
Does that make sense as a goal?
모두 동의하시죠?
Does everyone agree?
좋습니다.
OK.
좀 더 정확히 말하자면,
And more precisely,
basically, we
키와 값 행렬을 저장할 수 있는 방법을
찾는 것이 핵심입니다.
want to find a way for the key
and value matrices to be saved.
여기서 쿼리 부분은 강조하지 않고 있죠.
And I'm not
underlining the Q part
왜냐하면 쿼리는 항상
현재 토큰에 해당하는 것이니까요.
here because of course,
the query corresponding
이전 토큰들에 해당하는 쿼리는
현재 토큰에는 의미가 없으니까요.
to the previous
tokens are not going
그래서 키와 값이 더 중요하게 됩니다.
to be of interest for
the present token.
결국 키와 값 부분인 거죠.
So it's like the
key and value part.
좋습니다.
OK.
그래서 KV 캐시라는 개념이 있습니다.
So there is this concept
of KV cache, where
목표는 이 key와 value 행렬을 저장하는 것입니다.
the goal is to store
this key and value
어딘가에 이 행렬들을 저장해두고, 캐시에서 직접 재사용하는 거죠.
matrices somewhere, and reuse
them directly from the cache.
여기서 방금 설명한 것처럼,
So what I just
mentioned here, when
어떤 토큰을 계산할 때는
you want to compute
a given token,
key와 value를 다시 계산하지 않고
you would reuse the
key and the value
캐시에서 바로 꺼내서 사용하게 됩니다.
directly from the cache
instead of computing it again.
즉, 이게 바로 우리가 이야기한 개념을
So this is basically,
representation of what
구현한 예시라고 보시면 됩니다.
we just mentioned here.
이해되시나요?
Does that make sense?
네, 좋습니다.
OK.
아주 잘 따라오셨습니다.
Awesome.
자, 그럼 우리가 또 할 수 있는 것은 무엇이 있을까요?
So what else could we do?
네.
Yeah.
좋은 질문입니다.
Great question.
학습할 때도 KV 캐싱을 사용하나요?
So during training,
do we do KV caching?
학습에서는 보통 teacher forcing이라는 개념을
I would say during training,
you have this concept
활용합니다. 즉, 모든 입력을
of teacher forcing, where
you put all your inputs
한 번에 모두 모델에 넣어줍니다.
and pass it all
together at once.
그래서 학습할 때는 KV 캐싱이라는 개념이
So this concept of KV
caching doesn't even come up.
아예 등장하지 않습니다.
Yeah.
네, 좋은 질문이었습니다.
But great one.
네.
Yep.
네, 질문은 이 모든 걸 왜 하냐는 것이었죠?
Yeah so the question was,
what is the point of all this?
이미 수행한 연산을
다시 재사용하려는 겁니다.
We want to just reuse
the computations that
이미 계산된 결과를 다시 사용하는 겁니다.
were already done.
그리고 정답은 네, 맞습니다.
And then your answer is yes.
정확해요.
Spot on.
다른 질문 있는 분 있나요?
Any other questions?
좋습니다.
OK, great.
자, 이제 우리가 이런 값들을 캐시에 저장할 수 있다는 걸 봤으니,
So now that we have seen that
we could cache these quantities.
그럼 또 어떤 걸 해볼 수 있을까요?
So what else could we do?
지난주 강의에서 나왔던 내용 중에,
So is there something
from last week's lecture
혹시 우리가 다시 쓸 수 있는 방법이 있을까요,
that we could reuse,
maybe something
예를 들어 캐시의 키와 값의 양을 줄이는 방법이요.
that reduces the amount of
cache, the key and value?
이런 테크닉이 있을까요?
Do we have some techniques?
스파스 어텐션이요.
Sparse attention.
네, 그럴 수도 있죠.
Yeah, that could be.
그럴 수도 있는데, 여기서는 해당되지 않습니다.
That could be, but not here.
모든 토큰에 어텐션을 적용한다고 생각해 봅시다.
Let's say you're
attending to everyone
그리고 키와 값의 개수에 집중해 보세요.
and you focus on the
number of keys and values.
이 수를 줄일 방법이 있을까요?
Is there a way to
reduce this number?
정리하자면, 여기서 저는
So just to recap,
we have here, I'm
멀티헤드 어텐션을 기준으로 설명하고 있습니다.
operating in the context of
multi-head attention, which
여기서는 h개의 헤드를 사용하죠.
is you have your h heads.
즉, 쿼리 프로젝션이 h개 있고,
So you have h number
of query projections,
키 프로젝션, 값 프로젝션도 각각 h개가 있습니다.
h key projections,
h value projections.
지난주에 배운 기술 중에서
These are any technique
from last week
이 수를 줄일 수 있는 걸 다시 활용할 수 있을까요?
that we could reuse that
could reduce this number.
네.
Yeah.
네, 들었습니다.
I heard it.
네.
Yeah.
그룹 쿼리 어텐션입니다.
Group query attention.
맞아요, 정확합니다.
Yeah, exactly.
이번에는 키와 값을 묶어서 그룹화하는
So we had these concept of
grouping keys and values
함께 묶는 방식으로,
일반적인 공식화는
together, where basically the
general formulation is called
group query attention이라고 부릅니다.
여기서 이렇게 그룹핑을 하고,
group query attention, where
you group these, and then
외부 값 h와 1은 각각
the external values h and
1 denotes respectively
전체 멀티헤드 어텐션과
멀티 쿼리 어텐션을 의미합니다.
the full multi-head attention,
and then multi query attention.
그리고 최신 LLM 논문들에서
And then in modern day
LLMs, a lot of papers,
실제로 많은 경우 GQA, 즉
적절하게 정해진 그룹을 사용하는 방식을 씁니다.
they use GQA, with some
group that is sensible value.
그래서 이런 방식도
충분히 활용할 수 있습니다.
So this is also
something we can do.
좋습니다.
OK, great.
이제 조금 하드웨어 쪽
이야기로 넘어가 보겠습니다.
And now I'm going to go a
little bit into the hardware
주로 하드웨어 관점입니다.
side of things.
만약 이런 값들의 캐시를
추론 시점에 아주 단순하게 저장한다면,
So if we were to store the cache
for all these values in a naive
라고 가정해봅시다.
way, at inference time.
예를 들어,
So let's say you receive--
제가 인퍼런스 서버라고 하면,
so let's say I'm an
inference server,
여러 사용자로부터 쿼리를
받는 상황이 될 수 있겠죠.
I receive queries
from multiple users.
쿼리 1, 그리고 쿼리 2를
각각 받았다고 해 보겠습니다.
And let's say I receive a query
one and I receive a query two,
이때 키와 값 행렬을 저장하는
가장 단순한 방법은
a naive way of storing the
key and value matrices would
메모리의 일부 영역을
예약해 두는 것입니다.
be in reserving a
portion of the memory
초기에 전체 컨텍스트 길이에
해당하는 영역을 미리 배정하는 거죠.
at the beginning that correspond
to the entire context length,
언제 디코딩이 끝날지 모르기 때문입니다.
because you don't where
you're going to stop.
보통 디코딩은
EOS 토큰이 나올 때 멈추게 됩니다.
You're decoding because
you stop your decoding
EOS 토큰이 등장하면 디코딩이 종료되죠.
when you hit the EOS token.
그래서 전체 블록을 할당해야 하고,
So you would have
this whole block
이 블록의 크기는 컨텍스트 최대 길이만큼
확보해 놔야 합니다.
of size context
length, maximum context
최대 컨텍스트 길이의 메모리가
예약됩니다.
length that could be reserved.
이렇게 하면 메모리 낭비가
상당히 많이 발생합니다.
So one observation is that
it leads to a lot of waste.
예를 들어 컨텍스트 길이가 2k면,
So let's say if your context
length is of size like 2k,
각 쿼리마다 2k씩 별도로
메모리를 할당해 두는 셈입니다.
you have 2k reserved for
a given request 2k there.
그리고 동시에 더 많은 요청을 받으려면,
So at any given time, let's say,
you want to get more requests,
더 많은 요청을 처리하고 싶을 수도 있겠죠.
you want to serve more requests.
메모리가 아주 빠르게
부족해질 수 있습니다.
Your memory will
very quickly not
충분한 공간이 없어서
요청을 처리하지 못할 수 있죠.
have enough space
to accommodate Does
이런 제약이나 이슈가 이해되시나요?
these constraints or this
challenge make sense?
네.
Yeah.
좋습니다.
OK.
그리고 PagedAttention이라는 논문이 있습니다.
And then there is this paper
that is called PagedAttention.
이 논문에서는 여러 가지 개념을 정의합니다.
And it defines
several quantities.
예를 들어 reserved, internal fragmentation
같은 용어가 있습니다.
So there is this reserved
quantity internal fragmentation
또 external fragmentation도 있습니다.
and external fragmentation.
internal fragmentation은 기본적으로
Internal fragmentation
is basically
모델이 요청을 처리하기 위해
예약해 둔 공간을 의미합니다.
the space that is being
reserved by the model
이 공간이 요청을 완성하는 데 쓰이죠.
to complete the request.
그리고 reserved spot은
And the reserved spot
is the subset of it
실제로 사용된 토큰에 해당하는
공간의 일부입니다.
that corresponds to tokens
that were actually being used.
즉, 실제로 사용된
internal fragmentation 공간입니다.
So it's the kind of
space that's actually
내부적으로는 아무것도 없지만 공간만 예약된 상태죠.
used internal fragmentation.
실제로는 비어 있지만,
예약만 되어 있는 공간입니다.
There is nothing in there,
but it was reserved.
external fragmentation은
메모리 관리 시스템에서 발생합니다.
And external fragmentation is
the memory management system
이 시스템은 메모리 블록을
연속적으로 배치하지 않습니다.
that doesn't necessarily put
one block one after another,
대신 각자 방식으로 메모리 블록을 할당하죠.
but has its own way of
allocating memory blocks.
이렇게 하면 중간에 빈 공간이 생길 수 있습니다.
So it might leave
some other gaps.
그래서 이들은 이런 문제를 해결하기 위해
And they came up
with a system that
PagedAttention이라는 시스템을 고안했고,
is called a PagedAttention
that is powering
이 시스템은 vLLM이라는
추론 패키지에 적용되어 있습니다.
one inference package
called the vLLM that
이 패키지는 메모리 맵핑과 같이
생성 과정을 블록 단위로 처리해서 이 이슈를 해결합니다.
solves this issue by mapping,
like the generation process
즉, 정해진 크기의 블록으로 나누어 관리합니다.
by blocks of fixed size.
그렇게 하면 전체 메모리의 큰 부분을
한 번에 할당하지 않아도 됩니다.
So instead of allocating a
whole portion of the memory
각 요청마다 메모리를 세분화해서
작은 조각으로 관리하는 것이죠.
to answer a given
request, it breaks it down
더 작은 청크 단위로 쪼개서 할당하는 방식입니다.
by smaller chunks.
이 논문에서는 블록 값을 16으로 설정해 두었습니다.
So I think the paper takes
like a value of 16 for blocks.
보시는 것처럼, 예를 들어 생성 과정에 있다고 해봅시다.
So as you can see, let's say
you are in a generation process
어떤 한 행을 이미 사용했다면,
and you have used
a given row, you
그 다음에는 공간을 더 낭비하지 않고
바로 다른 행을 사용하게 됩니다.
would just start using
another row without wasting
즉, 그 이상의 공간을 낭비하지 않게 되는 거죠.
more space than that.
그리고 여기에는 어떤 딕셔너리가 있는데요,
And then you have
some dictionary
이 딕셔너리는 토큰의 위치 인덱스를
해당 캐시 값에 매핑합니다.
that maps token position indices
to basically their cache values.
이렇게 하면 캐시를 좀 더 효율적으로
관리할 수 있습니다.
So there is a smart
way of managing it.
논문에서는 이런 방식이 조각화를
상당히 줄여준다고 보여줍니다.
And they show that it reduces
fragmentation by quite a lot.
네, 그렇습니다.
Yeah.
좋습니다.
OK, great.
이제 이 KV 캐시를 가지고
다른 것도 살펴보겠습니다.
Now let's do something
else with this KV cache.
지금까지 내부 표현이
어떻게 구성되는지 봤죠.
So we just saw that you have
your internal representation
토큰의 내부 표현을 쿼리, 키, 값으로 프로젝트합니다.
of your token and you project
it into query, key, and value.
그리고 키와 값은 실제로,
And then key and
value is actually
무시할 수 없는 차원의 데이터를 가집니다.
something that is of a dimension
that is like non-negligible.
이것들을 각각의 트랜스포머 블록마다
저장해줘야 하죠.
And you need to store
each copies of it
그래서 이런 벡터들을 여러 개 기억해야 합니다.
in each transformer block.
여러 개의 벡터들을 관리해야 하는 상황이죠.
So you have many
of these vectors
이런 표현을 더 압축해서 저장할 수 있을까요?
that you need to keep track of.
이 주제는 DeepSeek에서
시도한 부분이기도 합니다.
And is there a way to make that
representation somehow more
표현을 좀 더 압축할 수 있는 방법이 있을지,
compact?
DeepSeek에서는 이런 개념을
다루기 위한 시도를 했습니다.
And this is a topic
that DeepSeek has tried
이 개념을 뭐라고 불렀냐면--
to tackle in a concept called--
'멀티-레이턴트 어텐션'이라고 부른 것 같습니다.
I think it was called
multi-latent attention.
이제 이 부분을 살펴볼 텐데요--
We're going to see--
먼저 기본적인 경우부터 알아보겠습니다.
so let's look at
the vanilla case.
멀티헤드 어텐션에서는,
If you are in
multi-head attention,
하나의 토큰 표현에 대해
then for a given
representation of a token,
h개의 프로젝션 매트릭스가 있어서,
각각이 키로 변환해줍니다.
you have h projection matrices
that turn it into a key.
여기에 다들 동의하시죠?
Does everyone agree with that?
이제 셀프 어텐션의 기본 수식에 대해
살펴보겠습니다.
So the kind of
self-attention formula,
키를 만들기 위한 프로젝션 행렬 Wk가
있고,
you have a projection
matrix wk for keys,
이 행렬은 토큰 표현을 어떤 키 공간으로
투영해줍니다.
that will project the token
representation into some key.
그리고 h개의 헤드가 있습니다.
And you have h heads.
프로젝션이 h번 일어나고,
You have h such
projections and you
그 결과 h개의 임베딩이 만들어지며,
have h such resulting
embeddings that you
이 임베딩들을 캐시에 저장해야 합니다.
need to store in your cache.
키뿐만 아니라 값도 동일하게
캐시에 저장해야 하기 때문입니다.
Because you have that for
keys, you have that for values.
즉, 굉장히 많은 벡터를 저장해야 합니다.
That's a lot of
vectors to store.
그리고 이렇게 저장되는 키와 값 역시
길이가 꽤 깁니다.
And these keys and values,
they are quite long as well.
이제 이 크기를 줄일 수 있는지
살펴보겠습니다.
So let's see if we
can make it smaller.
멀티 레이턴트 어텐션에서는
What multi-latent
attention does is
프로젝션 행렬을
중간 공간을 거쳐 인수분해합니다.
that it factorizes
these projection matrix
이 중간 공간은
into an intermediary
space that is
키 공간보다 더 낮은 차원입니다.
of lower dimension
than the space of keys.
먼저 차원을 줄여주는 변환이 있고,
You have a first
transformation that
그 다음에 다시 복원하는 변환이 이어집니다.
reduces the dimension
and then another one that
즉, 압축된 것을 다시 풀어줍니다.
decompresses it.
이런 식으로
가장 먼저 적용한 연산입니다.
So this is the first
operation that they
이렇게 하면 표현을 더 간결하게
만들 수 있습니다.
did in order to make the
representation more compact.
여기서 한 가지 더 똑똑한 점이 있습니다.
But they did something
else that is very smart.
바로 압축 행렬을
They said that the
compression matrix
키와 값에 대해서도
공유할 수 있다는 점입니다.
could be shared across
keys and values, which
즉, 특정 토큰 표현에 대해
캐시에 저장해야 할 내용이
says for a given token
representation, the cache
키와 값에 대해 동일해질 수 있습니다.
that you need to store for keys
and for values is the same.
단, 디컴프레션을 위한 행렬은
And then you would have
still different matrices
키와 값별로 다르게 두어서,
here for the decompression
part to actually learn
각각 키와 값의 표현을 다르게 학습합니다.
different representations
for a key and value.
여기서 하나의 간소화는
키와 값 모두에 대해 이를 공유하는 것입니다.
But one simplification
here has been to share it
즉, 키와 값에 대해 행렬을 공유하는 방식입니다.
for across keys and values.
그리고 더 나아가, 이걸 h개의 헤드 전체에도 공유할 수 있습니다.
And even better, share
it across the h heads.
즉, h개의 임베딩을 따로 두는 대신, 하나만 사용하게 됩니다.
So instead of having h such
embeddings, you have just one.
그리고 이 방법을 key에도 적용하고,
And then you do that for key.
value에도 똑같이 적용합니다.
You do that for value.
즉, 마지막에는 각각의 트랜스포머 블록마다
So at the end of it, for
every transformer block,
토큰마다 하나의 표현만 남게 됩니다.
you have a single
representation per token.
이해되시나요?
Does that make sense?
이렇게 하면 저장해야 할 것도 줄어들죠.
So not only you have
less things to store.
DeepSeek V2 논문에서는 이렇게 했을 때
The DeepSeek V2 paper also
showed a performance improvement
일종의 정규화 효과로 인해 성능이 개선된다고 보고했습니다.
that it's kind of credited
some regularization
이런 방식이 정규화 효과를 주었다고 볼 수 있습니다.
consequence of doing so.
그래서 좀 더 유용하고, key와 value에 공유될 수 있는
So it learns representations
that are maybe more useful
표현을 학습하게 됩니다.
and shared across
keys and values.
즉, 단순히 하드웨어적인 이점뿐 아니라
So apparently there is also
performance benefits to it that
성능 향상 효과도 확인된다는 것입니다.
is not just hardware based.
좋습니다.
OK, great.
이제 저희가 몇 가지를 살펴봤으니
So now we have seen some--
네.
Yeah.
질문이 들어왔는데, low rank 차원을 튜닝하냐는 것입니다.
So the question is, do you
tune the low rank dimension?
차원 자체는 설계상에서 결정하며,
So the dimension itself
is a design choice.
고정값입니다.
It's fixed.
또 다른 질문은, 모든 경우에 같은 low dimension을 쓰느냐는 것인데,
So the question is,
is it the same lower
네, 모두 같은 low dimension을 사용합니다.
dimension for everyone.
즉, 차원 크기는 고정되어 있고 모두 같게 설정됩니다.
So the dimension size is fixed
and is the same for everyone.
그렇다고 생각합니다.
I think.
하지만 이건 설계상의 선택입니다.
But it's a design choice.
다르게 설정할 수도 있지만, 실제로는 대부분
You could have different ones,
but I think in practice it
같은 크기로 설정하는 경우가 많습니다.
might be the same one.
네.
Yeah.
다른 질문 있으신가요?
Any other questions?
좋아요.
OK, great.
이제 10분도 채 남지 않았습니다.
So now we have less
than 10 minutes.
이제 출력 토큰 레벨에서 동작하는 기법들을 다루겠습니다.
We are going to cover techniques
that operate at the output
바로 토큰 레벨에서 적용되는 방법들입니다.
token level.
그리고 먼저 speculative decoding이라는 개념부터 살펴보겠습니다.
And then start with a concept
called speculative decoding.
이 방법은 매우 흥미로운 방식인데요,
That is a very
interesting method
작은 모델을 활용해서 더 큰 모델의 생성 과정을 돕는 방식입니다.
that uses some smaller model to
help the generation of a bigger
그리고 그 다음에 어떤 스킴을 사용해서
model, and then uses
some scheme that
출력 확률분포가 목표 모델과 일치하도록 만듭니다.
makes the distribution outputs
match one of the target one.
즉, 작은 모델을 활용해 먼저 생성하고,
So it uses a
combination of tricks
그 결과를 수학적 특성을 이용해 걸러내는 여러 트릭을 조합합니다.
of using a smaller model to
generate things, and then
이렇게 해서 확률분포가
gates it with some
mathematical based properties
큰 모델의 분포와 비슷해지도록 만드는 거죠.
to ensure we get a
distribution that
결국 결과 분포가 큰 모델의 분포처럼 보이게 됩니다.
looks the one of the big model.
그럼 이 방법의 아이디어를 설명하겠습니다.
So here's what is the
lectures, the mindset of it.
이제 우리가 좋아하는 예시로 다시 돌아가 볼게요.
So let's just come back
to our favorite example
바로 테디베어에 대한 예시입니다.
about teddy bears.
여기에서 여러분은 작은 모델에게,
So what you do is
that you ask a smaller
논문에서는 draft라고 부르는 모델에게 다음 단어를 생성하게 합니다.
model, that the paper calls
draft, to generate next words.
예를 들어, 'my teddy bear'라는 문장이 있다고 해봅시다.
So you have my teddy bear.
다음에 어떤 단어가 나올 수 있을까요?
What could be next words?
그래서 한 번 쭉 지나가면서,
So you have one pass.
토큰을 찾아냅니다.
You find token is.
여기서도 토큰이 하나씩 맞춰집니다.
You fit token is here again.
'귀엽다', '똑똑하다' 같은 토큰도 나옵니다.
You find cute and smart.
작은 LLM은 크기가 작아서, 이런 작업이
Since the LLM is small, this
is typically done faster than
큰 LLM에 비해 훨씬 빠르게 처리됩니다.
with the big LLM.
그리고 이 모든 결과가 나오면,
And then once you
have all of these,
작은 LLM이 예측한 토큰들을 다 모아서
you put the tokens that are
predicted by the smaller LLM
이렇게 예측된 모든 토큰을
타깃 LLM의 입력으로 넣습니다.
all as inputs to
the target's LLM.
여기서 타깃 LLM은 더 큰 모델,
즉 여러분이 실제로 사용하는 모델입니다.
That is like the bigger
model, like the one
이 모델을 통해
각 토큰의 확률분포를 생성하게 됩니다.
that you use, to
generate probability
이렇게 각 토큰마다
확률분포를 구하는 것이죠.
distributions for each of them.
그리고 이제 우리가 살펴볼 것은,
각 토큰의 출력 분포에 대해
And then we're going
to see that by having
일정한 규칙을 적용하면
some rule on the output
distribution of each
각 토큰의 확률분포를
시뮬레이션할 수 있다는 점입니다.
of these tokens, you can
simulate a probability
즉, 다음 토큰의
각 확률분포를 시뮬레이션할 수 있죠.
distribution of each token
of each next token that
그리고 이 확률분포는
타깃 모델의 분포와 닮게 됩니다.
looks one of the target models.
이 과정을 간단히 정리하면 이렇습니다.
So here's basically how it goes.
우선 토큰의 확률을 살펴봅니다.
So it looks at the
probability of the token
여기서 토큰은
드래프트 모델이 예측한 것입니다.
that the draft
model has predicted.
즉, 드래프트 모델의 확률이
So if the probability
of the draft model
드래프트 모델의 출력 분포에서
해당 토큰의 확률보다 크다면
is bigger than the one of the
draft model in the draft model's
그 토큰을 그냥 받아들이면 됩니다.
output distribution, then
you just accept the token.
그렇지 않은 경우에는
어떤 수용-거절 메커니즘을 사용합니다.
Otherwise, you have some
acceptance rejection mechanism
이 메커니즘을 통해 토큰을 받아들이거나
또는 거절하게 됩니다.
that either accepts the
token or rejects it.
모든 토큰이 수용된다고 가정해봅시다.
And let's say
everything is accepted.
그러면 한 번에 더 많은 토큰을
진행시킬 수 있게 됩니다.
Then in a single pass,
you are able to advance
[번역 실패] by way more tokens.
by way more tokens.
만약 실패하게 되면
다시 생성 과정을 이어가게 됩니다.
And then if it fails,
then basically you
즉, 그 좋은 토큰부터
생성을 재개하면서 확률분포를 조금 조정합니다.
resume the process of generation
from that good token onwards
[번역 실패] with some adjustments on the distribution.
with some adjustments
on the distribution.
여기까지 들으셨을 때, 여러분이 가질 수 있는 질문은
So one question that you
might ask from all of this,
'이거 그냥 어떤 레시피 같은 느낌인데...'
this looks like a recipe.
왜 이게 타깃 분포와 일치하는가
라는 점일 수도 있습니다.
Why is that matching
the target distribution?
전체 확률의 법칙에서 출발해서
So if you start from the
law of total probability
각 항을 이런 값들로 적어보면
and write each term
with these quantities.
결국에는 타깃 분포가
도출되는 것을 확인할 수 있습니다.
Then you will find the target
distribution at the end.
직접 한번 해보시길 권합니다.
So it's an exercise that
I encourage you to do.
그리고 이 슬라이드에 첨부된 논문에서는
And the paper that is
attached to the slide
여기서 몇 줄만에 그 과정을 보여줍니다.
here demonstrates it
in just a few lines.
그래서 아주 간단한 증명입니다.
So it's a very simple proof.
그리고 저는 이 증명이 정말 흥미롭다고 생각합니다.
And I think it's a very,
very interesting one.
이해되시나요?
Does that make sense?
네.
Yeah.
지금 질문은, 이것이 리젝션 샘플링인가요?
The question is, is
that rejection sampling?
네.
Yeah.
이미 이 방법을 아는 분들도 있을 겁니다.
So some of you might be
familiar with it already.
이해되시나요?
Does that make sense?
네.
Yeah.
그리고 제가 지금까지 말씀드리지 않은 한 가지가 있는데요,
And then one thing that
I didn't say is that
왜 마지막 토큰까지 여기에 넣었는가 입니다.
why did we even put
the last token here?
초안 토큰들을 모두 넣었고,
We put all the draft
tokens, but also
예측된 마지막 토큰까지 다 포함시켰죠.
the last one that
was predicted because
이렇게 모든 초안 토큰을 넣고 한 번만 forward pass를 하면,
by doing a single forward pass
with all these draft tokens,
그 다음 토큰의 확률분포를 자연스럽게 얻을 수 있습니다.
you get for free the probability
distribution of the token
그리고 나서 Qk+1에서 샘플링하면 되는 거죠.
that comes after that you can
then just sample from Qk plus 1.
이제 이런 방식의 근거를 짧게 정리해보겠습니다.
So just to give some
summary of the rationale.
단일 pass를 하는 비용은,
Doing a single pass is
as expensive as doing
한 번씩 따로 pass를 하는 것과 같습니다.
왜냐하면 추론 시에는
one pass at a time,
because at inference time,
메모리가 주로 병목이 되기 때문입니다.
you're memory bounds back.
즉, 연산이 아니라 메모리가 한계가 됩니다.
In other words, computations
are not the limiting factor.
결국 연산을 결정짓는 건
It's basically the
memory that will
바로 이 메모리 병목이죠.
bottleneck your computation.
그래서 더 작은 모델에서 이 작업을 하고,
So you want to do it
on a smaller model.
더 큰 모델에서는
And then on the
big model, you want
이 모든 확률 분포를 한 번에 계산하기를 원합니다.
to compute all of these
probability distributions
한 번에 모두 계산하는 것입니다.
at once.
이해되시나요?
Does that make sense?
좋습니다.
OK.
아주 좋습니다.
Great.
이제 마지막으로 한 가지 기법에 대해 말씀드리겠습니다.
And then I want to talk
about one last technique
이 기법은 멀티 토큰 예측(multi-token prediction)이라고 불립니다.
that is called
multi-token prediction.
이전 기법과 기본적으로 비슷한데요,
It's the same-- so by the
way, this previous technique
참고로 이전 기법은 speculative decoding이었습니다.
was called speculative decoding.
이번 기법도 사실 거의 비슷합니다.
And then this one is
basically doing the same.
약간 다르게 동작하긴 하지만요.
So it's doing slightly
a different thing.
하지만 draft 모델이 같은 모델 안에 내장되어 있습니다.
But the draft model is
embedded in the same model,
이 점이 매우 강력합니다.
which is very powerful.
즉, 이 모델은 마지막 디코더의 표현 위에 여러 개의 헤드를 추가한 구조입니다.
So basically, it's a model
that attaches multiple heads
마지막 디코더의 표현 위에 여러 개의 헤드를 붙인 모델입니다.
on top of the representation
of the last decoder.
과정은 이렇습니다. 학습 시에는
And the process here is
that at training time,
다음 단어 예측을 하지 않고,
it doesn't do next
word prediction.
여러 단어를 한 번에 예측합니다.
It does multi word prediction.
테스트 시에는 모든 헤드가 draft 모델 역할을 하게 됩니다.
And at test time, the draft
model is all your heads.
그리고 메인 모델은 첫 번째 헤드만 사용합니다.
And your main model is
just the first head.
이렇게 생성된 모든 draft 토큰을
So you have all
your draft tokens
다시 첫 번째 헤드에 넣어줍니다.
that you then feed
back to the first head
그리고 나서 수락 또는 거절(acceptance rejection) 과정을 거칩니다.
and then do
acceptance rejection.
그래서 논문에서는 이 과정을 greedy 방식으로 처리합니다.
So the paper does
it in a greedy way.
따라서 아까 말씀드린 수식으로 하지는 않습니다.
So it doesn't do it
with this formula.
아키텍처와 objective function이 바뀌었기 때문에,
Because since the architecture
and then the objective function
이전처럼 다음 토큰 예측 분포를 완전히 얻을 수 있는 성질은 없어집니다.
has changed, you don't have this
nice property of finding again,
즉, 다음 토큰 예측 분포를 다시 찾을 수 있는 좋은 특성이 사라집니다.
the next token
predictions distribution.
하지만 조금 변형된 방식으로 가능합니다.
But you have a slight
variation of it.
네, 그렇습니다.
And yeah.
멀티 토큰 예측에서 흥미로운 점 중 하나는 objective function의 변화입니다.
So like the interesting
notes out of the multi
멀티토큰 예측의 흥미로운 점은
목적 함수가 바뀐다는 것입니다.
token prediction is the
change in objective function.
그리고 두 번째로, 드래프트 모델과 타겟 모델이
And then second, the fact that
the draft model and the target
사실상 동일한 하나의 모델 안에 임베딩되어 있다는 점입니다.
model are basically
embedded in the same one.
따라서 두 모델을 굳이 분리할 필요가 없습니다.
So don't have to
separate the two.
네, 그렇습니다.
And yeah.
이 슬라이드 기억나시죠?
So you do remember this slide?
여기서 각각의 문제를
해결할 수 있는 기법들을 살펴봤습니다.
We have explored
techniques that can
각 항목에 맞는 기법들이 있습니다.
remedy each of these aspects.
그렇습니다.
So yeah.
관련 논문들도 꼭 한번 살펴보시길 추천합니다.
I highly recommend taking a
look at the associated papers
함께 읽어보시면 좋겠습니다.
as well.
이것으로 오늘 강의를 마치겠습니다. 감사합니다.
And with that,
thank you very much.